<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/all/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
        <atom:link href="https://shilohc.github.io/blog/all/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Food Is Hard</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/food_is_hard/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/food_is_hard/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The buying, making, and consuming of food is a very complex cognitive task.  To my unrelenting annoyance, I still have to eat multiple times, &lt;em&gt;per day&lt;/em&gt;, if I want to continue being alive and functional.  For those of you who have brains that work and don&amp;rsquo;t make every mildly complex task a major siege, I wanted to break down the whole food process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, of course, there is grocery shopping.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1211386.html&#34;&gt;Siderea has discussed this in the past.&lt;/a&gt;  (Sidenote: it is &lt;em&gt;so annoying&lt;/em&gt; to text-search Dreamwidth blogs.  I&amp;rsquo;m considering writing a scraper just so I can grep for Siderea Posts more easily.)  This post discusses the complexity problem of trying to make grocery lists when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to cook some amount of meals, and recipes require more than one food item, and a grocery store may be out of stock or have various sales that make this difficult, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t even get into one major problem I&amp;rsquo;ve had in the past: grocery stores shutting down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From January of 2017 until March of this year, I lived on MIT&amp;rsquo;s campus and cooked for myself.  In that time I had five different go-to grocery stores.  At first, I went to an enormous Star Market, which was (together with the Central Square H-Mart) the place where every MIT student got groceries.  When it shut down, the next-nearest grocery stores were all in Central.  I briefly tried schlepping to Central on a regular basis to shop at the Whole Foods a few blocks from the T stop (because H-Mart is not long on gluten-free options), but that used up a huge amount of energy, and I could only feasibly carry four grocery bags max (to say nothing of fridge space), so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t physically go grocery shopping frequently enough to keep myself fed.  So I started getting my groceries online from Whole Foods through Instacart, which worked so well that I bought a year of Instacart Premium for about $150 shortly before Instacart announced that since Amazon bought Whole Foods, Whole Foods would no longer be available on Instacart.  (If I could kill people psychically through the power of pure hatred, Jeff Bezos would no longer be with us.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I was forced to switch to Prime Now to get stuff from Whole Foods.  (I can&amp;rsquo;t now recall why Star Market/Instacart wasn&amp;rsquo;t an option, but there was &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; arbitrary food item I relied on at the time that they didn&amp;rsquo;t carry.  More on this later.)  Prime Now, however, was a much worse experience than Instacart, because (a) the groceries were split across a large quantity of grocery bags which never came with handles for some reason (???) and (b) apparently none of their exploited gig delivery workers understood street addresses well enough to reliably find me.  (I typically instructed them to deliver to Building 66, which has the address 25 Ames St.  I had one driver deliver to Building 25, another deliver to Building 14 for no reason I could figure out, and yet another attempt to drive &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; the campus&#39; facilities-only service roads.)  I was delighted when Brothers Marketplace opened up in Kendall Square, because it meant I could go physically grocery shopping again &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; having to wait for a day when I felt physically energetic yet could afford to wipe myself out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may seem pretty obvious, but shopping at a different grocery store means you have a different set of available foods.  Probably for someone who can cook from scratch more reliably than me, and who can eat normal foods instead of gluten-and-soy-free concoctions, and who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have massive sensory aversions to an apparently random set of common food ingredients, this is less of an issue.  But my brain works such that I depend on a small set of somewhat-rare items (goat cheese, a specific brand of microwave dinner, a specific brand of gluten-free crackers, etc), and whenever I switch to a grocery store that doesn&amp;rsquo;t have one of the items in the set, it materially restricts the variety of foods I can eat.  However, once an item disappears from my regular grocery rotation due to unavailability, I&amp;rsquo;m not very likely to remember it and look for it in a new grocery store.  Particularly if my new grocery store is online shopping, instead of going to the physical store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(As an example: I used to like getting gluten free frozen pizzas from Star Market way back in freshman year.  Then I switched grocery stores, and at some point in this process the only gluten free frozen pizzas I could find were either also soy cheese (gah) or were slimy/inedible for some other reason (cauliflower crusts seem to live on a spectrum from inedibly slimy to inedibly crumbly, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure there is a point where they become edible).  After a certain amount of time, energy, and money spent on bad frozen pizzas I gave up on the whole concept, and unthinkingly internalized that if I wanted to have a decent gluten free pizza I had to order from Domino&amp;rsquo;s or spend an hour in the kitchen making a pizza using a Chebe box mix crust.  Last week I spent a while going through &lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt; gluten free frozen meal available from Star Market on Instacart and ordered one of anything that looked good.  I accidentally bought some tofu curry which I can&amp;rsquo;t eat, but also I found a decent brand of gluten free frozen pizza again, so this week I pissed off my roommates by ordering six of them to cram into our freezer.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online grocery shopping sites are designed kind of like regular Amazon, except that I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to buy groceries in the same way that I buy soap and drinking glasses.  I can browse a physical grocery store much more easily, to see if there&amp;rsquo;s anything interesting I might want to pick up &amp;ndash; or if I remember that I got some chips I really liked last time, and I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the brand name but I do remember vaguely what the package looked like, I can find it again by wandering down the snack aisle.  Instacart (for example, although Prime Now is similar) is much less dense; it&amp;rsquo;s exhausting to scroll through a number of options that I&amp;rsquo;d be just fine with glancing past in a physical store.  In a physical store, it&amp;rsquo;s also pretty easy for me to pick up a different salsa in the salsa aisle on a momentary whim.  Online grocery shopping makes it super easy to just re-order the same stuff, but it&amp;rsquo;s much higher friction to try new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be cool if Instacart would take advantage of the Internet as a medium for cool UX, instead of being a place where I scroll through endless pictures of groceries?  What if it OCR&amp;rsquo;d the nutrition facts on all the items and never even showed me anything containing soy?  What if I could look at items and click either &amp;ldquo;Add to cart&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Try something new&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; which would show me other similar items, similar to the replacement recommendation engine?  What if the search results page crammed way, way more pictures of items on the screen, and didn&amp;rsquo;t show the name of the item until you hovered over it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh man, and I almost forgot the most annoying thing about online grocery shopping which is that you have to carefully select replacements for everything, and if enough stuff is out of stock and you&amp;rsquo;re not paying attention, the shopper will &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; end up buying you cookies &amp;lsquo;n cream ice cream, which, if you&amp;rsquo;re not aware, typically has gluten in it.  Multiple times since quarantine started, I&amp;rsquo;ve attempted to order 6 goat cheese logs and taken delivery for an equal quantity of mozzarella logs.  The whole point of goat cheese logs is that I can eat goat cheese on a cracker.  Experimentally, because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure what else to do with 6 mozzarella logs, I tried eating a big chunk of mozzarella on a cracker.  It was not a good experience.  I spent probably $100 on mozzarella logs that mainly ended up going moldy in the fridge before I thought to write &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t replace with mozzarella&amp;rdquo; in the Special Instructions section.  (Similar solution for the ice cream.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is beside the point.  There&amp;rsquo;s one other reason I was so excited about having Brothers Marketplace in Kendall, which I was able to enjoy for maybe three months.  (It opened in November of 2019.  I left for winter break in December, was gone for all of January of 2020, and returned to campus in February, then moved out of my room for good in mid-March.)  When you order groceries once a week from Instacart, or buy them once every two-to-four weeks when you can summon the energy to walk 20 minutes to Central, grocery shopping is a major siege that requires major planning.  When you can bop down to Brothers twice a week after class with a couple of career fair bags, you just need to buy what you feel like cooking and eating over the next three days.  I&amp;rsquo;m chronically incapable of meal-planning &amp;ndash; or rather, I can plan just fine, but I can&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;follow&lt;/em&gt; the plan for shit, because my energy levels and food tastes are so variable.  When I started shopping at Brothers, I wasted &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much less food &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;d just buy what I needed to cook three meals&amp;rsquo; worth of something.  I stopped buying salmon filets to rot in my fridge and started buying them only when I immediately intended to make baked salmon.  Forgetting something on the grocery list wasn&amp;rsquo;t an issue, either, because I could just go back.  As many times as I needed.  It&amp;rsquo;s like the programming thing where your workflow materially changes when your build takes 2 seconds, as opposed to 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m back to ordering from Star Market via Instacart, because we all live in COVID hell and at any rate now I live in Somerville.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think we&amp;rsquo;ve adequately explored the many ways that grocery shopping sucks.  However, this is only half the battle; doing something with the food once you have it also sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1238508.html#cutid1&#34;&gt;cooking is actually a really complex problem&lt;/a&gt;.  That post breaks it down into 36 (!) steps &lt;strong&gt;starting with the assumption that you have already gotten groceries&lt;/strong&gt;.  And note how many of those 36 steps involve further planning and breaking down into steps, depending on the recipe and the amount of space and equipment you have (for example, &amp;ldquo;If your appliances will need to be deployed from storage, pull them now and figure out where they will go in your cooking space.  If they will not all fit at once, figure out what you will be doing for staging.&amp;quot;)  If you have executive dysfunction, every task needs to be broken down into &lt;strong&gt;at least&lt;/strong&gt; this level of detail &amp;ndash; and even the simplest 36-step process, which this definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t, is not something I can be relied upon to do on any kind of regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other reason I can&amp;rsquo;t be relied upon to cook on a regular basis is because cooking is an enormous energy sap, and (say it with me) my day-to-day energy levels are deeply unpredictable.  Processing ingredients always seems to put weird strain on my back muscles.  Being in a hot room makes me tired incredibly quickly &amp;ndash; so much for preheating the oven.  Let&amp;rsquo;s not even discuss the specially-crafted hell of doing dishes when both dish noises and touching wet food bits are massive sensory triggers.  So I&amp;rsquo;ve never once in my life been able to successfully make and then execute a meal-plan.  Unfortunately, it seems like the only alternative is to buy a bunch of food ingredients on speculation that you might be able to do something with them eventually and then watch them turn to mush in your fridge.  Also, if something has been in the fridge too long, I will stop seeing it as an item I could potentially use and start seeing it as just another piece of furniture (right up until the time I wonder why my fridge has started smelling so bad).  I never really have any idea what food is or is not available if it&amp;rsquo;s not immediately visible when I open up the fridge.  This applies also to the food that I cook for myself; I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to describe to you the feeling of impotent rage at my own incompetence I get when I realize that, of the three tupperwares full of food I sacrificed all my energy to generate two Saturdays ago, one of them is still in the fridge and has grown mold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My great smart fridge idea, which anyone reading this is welcome to steal, is this: It&amp;rsquo;s not connected to the internet at all.  It just lets you scan barcodes or take pictures of all the food you put in, and all the food you take out, and maintains a list of what you have and how long it&amp;rsquo;s been in there.  Maybe it even lets you know what stuff is about to expire.  I literally don&amp;rsquo;t need my fridge to order food for me, or suggest recipes, but I would desperately love to have a fridge that maintains its own inventory.  I&amp;rsquo;ve strongly considered buying a raspberry pi and duct-taping a webcam to the side of the fridge and rolling my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have that, I mostly try not to get any food that needs to be cooked, particularly in a timely fashion.  (I love making baked salmon, because it&amp;rsquo;s delicious and pretty easy to cook &amp;ndash; but I hardly ever manage to cook a piece of salmon before it goes bad.)  I mostly eat microwave dinners and cheese-and-crackers and yogurt and scrambled eggs (and ice cream whenever I notice I&amp;rsquo;m not getting a lot of calories), and whenever I order delivery food I get another meal worth of leftovers.  And sometimes I try to cook myself a few meals of food in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The many, many restrictions on my food intake tend to lead me towards eating the same foods a lot.  On one level, I like this.  Less decision fatigue is good.  On another level, it gets really boring sometimes.  On a third level, sometimes if I eat a food too many times it suddenly and arbitrarily becomes a sensory trigger and I can no longer even think about eating it without getting a little nauseous (typically this happens the moment I realize it&amp;rsquo;s a great food that should be one of my staples and stock up).  This is why I can no longer eat Mealsquares or liquid eggs or canned refried beans or tuna salad or peanut butter or smoked salmon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, it occurs to me that you may not know what a sensory trigger is!  It&amp;rsquo;s not the same as being a picky eater.  Imagine, if you will, that you are in the hospital for three months, and the only things you are allowed to eat during this time are Jell-O and chicken broth.  Now imagine your reaction if, after this, someone tried to make you eat Jell-O.  Now imagine that you&amp;rsquo;re me, and this is just how you feel about a wide range of random food including potatoes and hamburgers and pork chops, for no readily apparent reason.  And I keep accidentally sensitizing myself to more and more food because the range of food that I can reliably acquire and eat is too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine that every time you try to explain the depth of this problem to someone, they get angry after you shoot down 1-3 of their &amp;ldquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t you just&amp;quot;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that despite the ADHD and the chronic fatigue and the dietary restrictions due to my chronic illness and the dietary restrictions due to my sensory issues, I do still have one important form of privilege here: I don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry too much about my food budget.  I&amp;rsquo;m a programmer, which means that I can semi-afford to live off gluten-free microwave dinners and delivery food and gluten-free frozen pizzas and fancy-ass yogurt/goat cheese.  (According to YNAB, my average monthly grocery spend is around $500, plus $200 for delivery food.)  If I had to live off disability, I&amp;rsquo;d quite likely starve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is, I&amp;rsquo;m always kind of on the knife&amp;rsquo;s edge of giving myself an eating disorder.  I try to stay fairly vigilant to this tendency because it&amp;rsquo;s not like I really need &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; mental health issue, but&amp;hellip; *gestures exhaustedly at above post*.  It&amp;rsquo;s easy, and in fact incredibly tempting, for me to skip meals, because unless I eat at consistent times my hunger response doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully work right.  Sometimes it does nothing, and I just forget to eat.  Sometimes it makes me feel tired and sad, which is not exactly conducive to summoning the energy to cook.  Sometimes it makes me nauseous; it&amp;rsquo;s as if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying attention at ALL in &amp;ldquo;how to run a digestive system&amp;rdquo; class.  Accidentally failing to eat is my natural state of existence.  Also, wow, turns out our culture really values skinniness, and since I&amp;rsquo;m trans and already not a huge fan of my body, you can start to see why the mindset where instead of pathetically failing at a basic human activity I&amp;rsquo;m being Virtuous by not eating is so attractive.  (&lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; I recently started Adderall, which is notoriously appetite-suppressing.)  Fortunately, turns out you kind of need to eat food to have any energy whatsoever, and I do need energy to do other things, so I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to stay out of the eating disorder zone thus far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that&amp;rsquo;s about the best I can say for my own ability to eat.  Very slowly and gradually, I&amp;rsquo;m getting better at food.  I&amp;rsquo;m figuring out more and more meals that I can actually make regularly.  One of my roommates does the dishes (before this, I measured every meal by how many dirty dishes it generated), and the other one contributed an Instant Pot to our lineup of kitchen equipment.  I also bought a wok, which I think of as essentially a big frying pan for making big batches of sludge.  (I eat a lot of sludge.  You can make one of my favorite sludges by following &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.budgetbytes.com/skillet-meatballs-and-marinara/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; meatballs recipe, except don&amp;rsquo;t form the meat into balls, just dump it all in the frying pan and dump pasta sauce over it once it&amp;rsquo;s browned.)  There are some interesting-looking grocery stores near my new apartment that I&amp;rsquo;m excited to try out, once the pandemic has died down enough that I feel safe going to a grocery store again.  Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll build the smart fridge; for now, one of my roommates goes through our fridge to toss old food and make an inventory every couple weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I keep iterating, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty confident that at some point I&amp;rsquo;ll get this shit figured out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this topic interests you, you should also read &lt;a href=&#34;https://theunitofcaring.tumblr.com/post/176275091706/san-francisco-is-trying-to-ban-employers-from&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; unitofcaring post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously I have more issues with food than just dietary restrictions, but dietary restrictions alone (your classic allergies, lactose/gluten intolerance, etc.) still significantly increase the cognitive load of getting food in a way that I would classify as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://aspire-to-the-light.tumblr.com/post/188434331847&#34;&gt;microdisability&lt;/a&gt;.  (Another example &lt;a href=&#34;https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-05-23-09:31.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that links to some great but not-super-relevant posts.)  A surprising amount of stuff has soy in it &amp;ndash; and if you&amp;rsquo;re at a restaurant or something that doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide an ingredient list, you have to either have all those things memorized or ask your waiter, who might fuck with you if they don&amp;rsquo;t believe you &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; have a dietary restriction.  If you don&amp;rsquo;t have any dietary restrictions yourself, you might find it interesting to try avoiding one or two of the top 8 allergens for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has just now occurred to me that this is part of why I get so angry when people try to feed me salad at food events because it&amp;rsquo;s the only everything-free option.  I mean, I also don&amp;rsquo;t like salad, but the main problem is that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;not food&lt;/em&gt;.  It is not &lt;em&gt;filling&lt;/em&gt;.  It will not appreciably decrease the amount of other food I need to eat.  It is not an appropriate substitute for an actual &lt;em&gt;meal&lt;/em&gt;.  It does not contain enough calories to be worth the trouble to choke down.  New rule: a gluten-free alternative meal is not an actual alternative unless it actually provides roughly the same number of calories as the original meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somerville has the best demonym I&amp;rsquo;ve ever heard, which is &amp;ldquo;Somervillain&amp;rdquo;.  Sucks to suck, Michiganders. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Yes, I Could Be Punctual If I Tried, But I Just Love Inconveniencing Others!</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/punctuality/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/punctuality/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://defector.com/be-on-time-for-things/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; is making the rounds of some blogs I read, who have linked to it with approval.  To be fair, it is pretty funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also just about made my blood boil, and I think I need to explain why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a neurobehavioral disorder that makes it very difficult for me to plan out what I need to do to get to a place on time.  I don&amp;rsquo;t really know how long tasks take, even tasks that I do a lot, until I&amp;rsquo;ve timed them, with a timer or with my watch.  But even if I have that, I may not have a full expansion of everything-that-needs-to-happen-before-I-leave.  I may have a vague sense of &amp;ldquo;oh I&amp;rsquo;ll pack my backpack and then I can go&amp;rdquo;, but there are also totally unexpected steps like putting on shoes and a jacket that I forgot to include in this plan, and therefore they&amp;rsquo;re not part of the time estimate.  So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really help to know the door-to-door time; there needs to be some buffer, but computing how much of it there should be is not a thing my brain will do on any mode other than full manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know being on time for things is one of the most basic adult skills, I know it&amp;rsquo;s how you show respect to people, I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; this already.  I want to be on time for things.  I &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be a reliable person who doesn&amp;rsquo;t rudely hold everything up.  I have put so much fucking effort into getting better at being on time for things &amp;ndash; whenever I put something on my calendar that I need to leave the house for, I ask Google Maps how long it will take me to get there, and multiply that number by around 1.5, and add 10-15 minutes to account for it ~mysteriously~ taking me longer than I expect to get out the door, and I block out that time for travel and then give it four different calendar alerts.  I have alarms on my phone and alarms on my smartwatch and alarms on my calendar and even alarms on my alarm clock (actually, alarms on three different alarm clocks) so that I get to things on time.  When I lived on campus, I lived in a dorm that was a 2-3 minute walk to most of the EECS buildings, because &amp;ldquo;oh shit it&amp;rsquo;s 10 I need to leave for my 10AM class that actually starts at 10:05&amp;rdquo; is simple enough that my brain can reason about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m still very frequently late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My neurobehavioral disorder also makes it hard for me to start or stop tasks, where &amp;ldquo;tasks&amp;rdquo; is defined as nearly everything a human does in the course of a day; on the other hand, dead (unoccupied) time is so horrible I&amp;rsquo;ll slide off within thirty seconds to go do something else.  So the calendar alerts need to hit at &lt;strong&gt;just&lt;/strong&gt; the right time, so that I have enough time to stop whatever I&amp;rsquo;m doing but not enough time to get distracted by something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am constantly paranoid that I have forgotten something.  I hate trying to get work done in days when I have meetings partly because they break my flow but mostly, if we&amp;rsquo;re being honest, because at least 20% of my brain is occupied in having anxiety about missing the meeting.  But if I do manage to distract that part of my brain, I will be late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you figured out yet that I&amp;rsquo;m talking about ADHD?  Time-agnosia is one of the most common symptoms of Goofy Dipshit Disorder, of Trouble Sitting Still Disorder, of Inconvenience-to-Real-Adults Disorder, of I Know I&amp;rsquo;m Incredibly Annoying So I&amp;rsquo;d Better At Least Be Funny Or I Will Have Literally No Friends Disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And before you ask, yeah, I also suck at making phone calls.  And sending emails.  And doing laundry (there are so many opportunities to totally forget about it, all of which will end up in it mouldering or getting wrinkled or thrown all over the floor by someone else who understandably wanted to use the laundry machine and got tired of waiting for me).  And following up on not receiving things.  And maintaining any organization system for my physical crap that doesn&amp;rsquo;t include at least three boxes of Misc Stuff and Stuff That Lived On My Desk Until I Realized I Barely Had Any Room For My Pad Of Paper And Then I Arbitrarily Scooped It Into This Box and I Don&amp;rsquo;t Know Why I Have This Stuff But I Can&amp;rsquo;t Throw It Out.  And remembering literally anything that isn&amp;rsquo;t written down before it blows up dramatically in my face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten very good at writing things down.  My Google Calendar is terrifying and if you even &lt;em&gt;contemplate&lt;/em&gt; messing with my Asana categories and tags I will bite a chunk out of your arm.  I&amp;rsquo;ve taken so many notes about everything at every internship I&amp;rsquo;ve ever done, and I recently got complimented on being so &amp;ldquo;organized&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;having everything written down&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;remembering stuff from last meeting&amp;rdquo;.  You wanna know my secret?  It&amp;rsquo;s a notebook, but the secret behind &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is that if writing everything down in a notebook was a Hot Tip that made every single adult in your life suddenly not hate your guts  when you were a kid, you&amp;rsquo;d get really good at it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how many times my mom got mad at me for asking, in the car, &amp;ldquo;By the way, where are we going?&amp;rdquo;  Because of course she would have told me my whole schedule for the day verbally when I was already in the car without anything to take notes with, and of course it went in one ear and out the other.  I was a kid at the time and I internalized that it was my fault for not being able to bully my brain into remembering things it is constitutionally incapable of remembering.  I know now that the difference between me and my mom is not that I am Just Not Trying Hard Enough, it&amp;rsquo;s that she has enough executive function for 3 people and I have enough executive function for maybe 0.4 people on a good day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already, and I cannot stress this enough, am aware that I have Inconvenience to Adults Disorder.  I strive harder to be on time than you will ever realize and I will still very frequently be late.  How neurotypical, and I say this with as much disdain as I can muster, to think that if I just &amp;ldquo;cared more about other people&amp;rdquo; I would inconvenience them less!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, why am I even trying to write about this?  theunitofcaring already said it better in three sentences way back in 2015:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“you’re late every time and it makes me feel like this doesn’t matter to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no it’s okay I’m late for airplanes and final exams and job interviews too.  the broken part is the part where ‘this matters’ is supposed to connect to ‘this happens’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://theunitofcaring.tumblr.com/post/120035888161/youre-late-every-time-and-it-makes-me-feel-like&#34;&gt;theunitofcaring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hang on, you may say, the original article wasn&amp;rsquo;t even &lt;em&gt;talking&lt;/em&gt; about people like you, who are still trying your Best.  It&amp;rsquo;s talking about people who call themselves &amp;ldquo;freewheeling&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;whimsical&amp;rdquo; as an excuse for being late all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have one thing to say to this:  When you have Will Not Be On Time Disorder, you can do one of two things.  You can put massive and draining amounts of your already limited energy into being on time anyway.  You can constantly work to &amp;ldquo;get better&amp;rdquo; at it, and apologize to people when (not if, but when) you fail, and hope they cut you some slack because you&amp;rsquo;re at least Trying.  (And &lt;em&gt;oh boy are you Trying.&lt;/em&gt;  But at what cost?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you can just give up and take the social consequences, because you know already that you&amp;rsquo;re probably going to fail, so why bother?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really, truly can&amp;rsquo;t blame anyone for deciding that the price of Option A is too high.  I truly can&amp;rsquo;t blame anyone for picking option B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what the article has to say about people who pick option B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;she is a fully Jokerfied sicko&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to leave room for the possibility that Jessica is being funny, here&amp;hellip; The alternative—the absolute only alternative—is that Jessica is an asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are late to that thing, and that thing cannot proceed until you arrive, you are imposing yourself on those other people’s time. [&amp;hellip;] [T]hey, unlike you, feel some bare-minimum responsibility for how their actions affect other people, whom they consider real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, sorry, I forgot those.  Jessica (or in this case Shiloh) Is An Asshole Disorder.  Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Feel Any Responsibility For How Their Actions Affect Others Disorder.  When I am constitutionally incapable of doing something, and I tell you that, but to your tiny little mind the something is &lt;em&gt;so easy&lt;/em&gt; that you simply &lt;em&gt;cannot process&lt;/em&gt; the idea that I am constitutionally incapable of doing it, you assume that I am making the conscious choice to not do the something on purpose, probably to annoy and victimize you specifically, because I am an asshole.  The only possible answer is that I am an asshole.  Because, and let me reiterate this, of a neurobehavioral disorder; having the brain that I was born with makes me an asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well!  I&amp;rsquo;ll certainly take that one under consideration.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few loose change thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that there are two main responses to being societally expected to do something that&amp;rsquo;s incredibly difficult for you, and that these responses can be summarized as &amp;ldquo;expend way too much energy trying to do it anyway&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;give up&amp;rdquo;, is something I&amp;rsquo;ve also seen mentioned in other aspects of ADHD.  From ADDitude, on Rejection Sensitive Dysphoria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People with ADHD cope with this huge emotional elephant in two main ways, which are not mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They become people pleasers. They scan every person they meet to figure out what that person admires and praises. Then they present that false self to others. Often this becomes such a dominating goal that they forget what they actually wanted from their own lives. They are too busy making sure other people aren’t displeased with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They stop trying. If there is the slightest possibility that a person might try something new and fail or fall short in front of anyone else, it becomes too painful or too risky to make the effort. These bright, capable people avoid any activities that are anxiety-provoking and end up giving up things like dating, applying for jobs, or speaking up in public (both socially and professionally).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; ADDitude, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.additudemag.com/rejection-sensitive-dysphoria-and-adhd/&#34;&gt;Rejection Sensitive Dysphoria and ADHD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I&amp;rsquo;m kind of skeptical of &lt;a href=&#34;https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/08/14/ssc-survey-results-adhd-and-rejection-sensitivity/&#34;&gt;RSD as it is commonly theorized to exist&lt;/a&gt;.  In particular, these two social outcomes seem like a really natural outgrowth of most authority figures, during your childhood, defaulting to disliking you over something that was mostly out of your control.  There&amp;rsquo;s the approach of trying really hard to get them to like you anyway, and the approach of giving up and trying to at least not be very noticeable.  (Becoming the class clown or a freewheeling Bohemian or whatever should be seen here as another endpoint of the &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo; approach that I&amp;rsquo;m really frustrated the ADDitude article fails to mention, especially since it&amp;rsquo;s, like, &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; stereotypical ADHD presentation.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really wanted to fit in this quote, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get the post to flow right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to silence my most reliable way of gathering, processing, and expressing information, I need to put more effort into controlling and deadening and reducing and removing myself second-by-second than you could ever even conceive, I need to have quiet hands, because until I move 97% of the way in your direction you can’t even see that there’s a 3% for you to move towards me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; juststimming, &lt;a href=&#34;https://juststimming.wordpress.com/2011/10/05/quiet-hands/&#34;&gt;Quiet Hands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is &amp;ndash; just such a perfect statement of the THING, where neurotypical people &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Typical_mind_fallacy&#34;&gt;typical-mind&lt;/a&gt; themselves into not even realizing that your problem is a possible thing that could go wrong with the human brain, and all of their &amp;ldquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t you just&amp;rdquo; suggestions inevitably presuppose that the missing link in your brain works, because they can&amp;rsquo;t really imagine it &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; working, what would that even be like?  And these are the majority of the people you encounter in life, so the &amp;ldquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t you just&amp;quot;s are like sandpaper, and after a while even the most kindly meant &amp;ldquo;why don&amp;rsquo;t you just&amp;rdquo; hits you where you&amp;rsquo;re raw and makes you strongly consider switching careers to arson.  But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get into a digression about Quiet Hands, and unusual methods of information processing that the traditional school system (and broader society, but schools tend to be the most aggressively authoritarian about it) deals with in awful, harmful, abusive ways, and all that, so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the other things I got reprimanded about was that I was always doodling or sketching in class when I should&amp;rsquo;ve been &amp;ldquo;paying attention&amp;rdquo;.  Doing something with my hands, for me, is a &lt;strong&gt;prerequisite&lt;/strong&gt; for paying attention; optimally I would knit or something, but if the only thing you&amp;rsquo;ll let me have is a piece of paper and a pencil, well, don&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if it turns into doodling.  But apparently full-page sketches are &amp;ldquo;distracting to the other students&amp;rdquo; (why do the other students care?  Why are they so invested in the contents of my notes that the lack thereof is a distraction?) and Not To Be Borne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a lot less of a big deal than Quiet Hands, but the principle is: the behavior you might find distracting might be the thing another person &lt;strong&gt;needs&lt;/strong&gt; in order to process the information they are trying to take in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, one reason why I blog a lot about disability, and why I try to include as many examples as possible in those posts, is that I want to share with you some small part of the fantastic diversity of ways in which people experience the world.  I think the best way to combat the typical mind fallacy is through lots and lots of training data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Captain-Awkward-ism.  Example usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Huh, thanks, I’ll think about it.” (This is not a lie, you will think about it and then not do it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://captainawkward.com/2020/07/08/1281-every-conversation-with-my-mom-is-an-interrogation-of-my-life-choices/&#34;&gt;Captain Awkward&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
 &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Visualize Everything</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/visualization/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/visualization/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the best things you can do for yourself, debugging-wise, is visualization &amp;ndash; this is especially true in robotics, where we deal nearly exclusively with things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the physical world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cameras and other sensors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;algorithms like localization, mapping, and path planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;humans and their activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip; and other stuff with physical meaning that you can look at&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all of these cases, it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to understand what&amp;rsquo;s going on if you slap your bizarre data that makes no sense in a picture, plot, or 3D visualizer.  It&amp;rsquo;s easy to draw on images with OpenCV.  It&amp;rsquo;s easy to publish stuff to rviz.  Unfortunately, it feels a lot harder than just printing a bunch of floats and trying to do the mental math yourself to check if they make sense.  This post is partially a reminder to me: it takes like 10 minutes tops to add a debug visualization; you are bad at mental math and after 10 minutes of trying to do it you will not have nearly as much insight as the visualization will give you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important point: the whole purpose of debug visualizations is that you have a confusing thing and you want to look at a picture of it, with as few conversion layers as possible so there&amp;rsquo;s no room for bugs to sneak in.  For example, if you&amp;rsquo;re trying to debug the conversion between image coordinates and some other quantity&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to convert your thing &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; to image coordinates to draw it on an OpenCV image, since the conversion is what&amp;rsquo;s not working in the first place.  Instead, try rviz if your output quantity is 3D points, or matplotlib if it&amp;rsquo;s two-dimensional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.opencv.org/2.4/modules/core/doc/drawing_functions.html&#34;&gt;Documentation for OpenCV draw functions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation for the &lt;code&gt;visualization_msgs&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.ros.org/visualization_msgs&#34;&gt;package&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;visualization_msgs/Marker&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.ros.org/api/visualization_msgs/html/msg/Marker.html&#34;&gt;message&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debugging over SSH, or for some other reason can&amp;rsquo;t use rviz?  Try &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dheera/rosshow&#34;&gt;rosshow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you happen to be using a RealSense, the Intel RealSense SDK also comes with a terminal-based tool for &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.intelrealsense.com/docs/rs-depth&#34;&gt;visualizing depth data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The usual debug flow using images in ROS is to publish images with debug info drawn on them to a new &lt;code&gt;xyz_debug&lt;/code&gt; image topic, then view them using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.ros.org/image_view&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;image_view&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.ros.org/rqt_image_view&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rqt_image_view&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most basic possible usage of &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; to plot two-dimensional data, here given as &lt;code&gt;xs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ys&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#666;font-weight:bold;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#666;font-weight:bold;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
plt.plot(xs, ys)
plt.show()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the docs for &lt;a href=&#34;https://matplotlib.org/3.2.1/api/_as_gen/matplotlib.pyplot.plot.html#matplotlib.pyplot.plot&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;plot&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more info, particularly about format strings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more complex &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; tasks, it usually becomes necessary to use figures and axes (explained &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/towards-artificial-intelligence/day-3-of-matplotlib-figure-axes-explained-in-detail-d6e98f7cd4e7&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#666;font-weight:bold;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;matplotlib.pyplot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;font-weight:bold&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#666;font-weight:bold;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;plt&lt;/span&gt;
fig = plt.figure()
axes = fig.add_subplot()
axes.plot(xs, ys)
plt.show()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I swear I&amp;rsquo;ve lost years of my life to image-related conversions.  For some reason nobody can agree on where the X and Y axes should go, what rows and columns and width and height mean, and what order the R, G, and B should go in.  Today for my internship I wrote a function that converts from [REDACTED] image coordinates to OpenCV image coordinates, and the X and Y axes are swapped but also for some reason one of them is backwards?  I&amp;rsquo;m only confident I got it right because the pink circle I&amp;rsquo;m drawing on the output image is in the correct place.  At least when you forget to convert BGR &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; RGB it&amp;rsquo;s pretty immediately noticeable. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>You Should Learn To Sew</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/sewing/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/sewing/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What are the most important General Life Skills that everyone should know?  Or, to put it another way, if you could design the ideal Home Ec class, and Home Ec classes existed anymore, what would you teach?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, cooking, probably.  How to clean the bathroom and do the dishes and wash your clothes.  Enough general handyperson skills that you can put together flat-pack furniture and hang curtains and wall art and do minor repairs.  If you have a bike or car, you should probably know how to maintain it, or at least what symptoms mean you should take it into the shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that you should also know how to sew.  By hand, with a needle and thread, because sewing machines are expensive and hard to store, but a needle and a spool of thread you can take anywhere.  Why?  Well, you wear clothes, right?  Just like you should probably know how to maintain your bike or car if you have one, you should probably know how to make basic clothing repairs, many of which are easy and quick enough that you can do them by hand in an evening after watching like 2 YouTube videos.  Adding patches to holes, reattaching belt loops and buttons, adding pockets to tragically under-pocketed womens&#39; pants, making minor alterations like hemming pants and sleeves&amp;hellip; if you&amp;rsquo;re feeling ambitious, you could also do slightly harder alterations like taking things in at the waist, but that&amp;rsquo;s out of scope for this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m hand-sewing, I use a nice big sewing needle with a nice big eye that&amp;rsquo;s easy to thread.  It may in fact be an embroidery needle.  I use a spool of white mercerized cotton thread that I inherited from my grandma, along with the rest of her sewing supplies, because it&amp;rsquo;s very strong.  You may want to get other colors of thread, like black and denim-blue, depending on what color your clothes are and how much you care about matching, but don&amp;rsquo;t compromise on strength.  If you want to fix a specific item that&amp;rsquo;s a weird color, take it into your local store that sells sewing supplies so you can find a color-matching thread.  Or, you know, if you don&amp;rsquo;t care that much you can just use white thread for everything, like me.  You may also want a seam ripper, some straight or safety pins (I recommend safety if you have to pick one kind), and sewing scissors (these will dull rapidly if you cut paper with them, so keep them separate from your normal scissors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will want to know how to do a running stitch and a backstitch.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B5tC06IXOKc&#34;&gt;Bernadette Banner can show you how.&lt;/a&gt;  She uses very tiny needles and stitches; I am lazy, so I use (as mentioned above) a big chonker of a needle and long ugly stitches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For additional strength, I typically sew with the thread doubled-up, which as a bonus makes it impossible for the needle to come unthreaded.  Cut a length of thread, thread the needle, then move the needle to the middle of the length of thread and tie the ends together.  When you start sewing, put this knot on the wrong side of your work (the side where you&amp;rsquo;re less worried about aesthetics, typically the back), but don&amp;rsquo;t pull it all the way tight against the fabric; leave a small loop.  After you&amp;rsquo;ve made your first stitch, thread the needle through the loop.  This makes a nice strong knot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to sew a patch:  Cut a piece of fabric from a material that won&amp;rsquo;t fray on the edges (this way you don&amp;rsquo;t need to finish the edges).  It should be a little larger than the hole all the way around &amp;ndash; this is called a &amp;ldquo;seam allowance&amp;rdquo; because it&amp;rsquo;s the extra room you need for the seam to go in.  If you have pins, pin the patch fabric in place.  If you don&amp;rsquo;t, depending on where the hole is you can use magnets or paperclips or just go without.  Stitch all the way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get special denim-patterned patches for denim jeans, which you would probably want to put on the outside.  However, I also patched one of the holes in my jeans using a piece of black scrap fabric with shiny rainbow dots on it, which I put on the inside of the jeans so it shows through the hole.  There&amp;rsquo;s no rules!  Do whatever!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to add a pocket, or make an existing but stupidly small pocket larger:  Get a pocket lining material (should be thin-ish so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t add too much bulk and optimally not stretchy; I&amp;rsquo;d recommend some kind of woven cotton but I have also cut pocket material out of a career fair t-shirt that was too small).  Decide how big you want your pocket to be &amp;ndash; measure your phone or hand or whatever if you&amp;rsquo;re not sure.  Add half an inch of seam allowance all the way around.  Cut out two of those shapes.  If it&amp;rsquo;s a rectangular pocket, you can also cut out one big long rectangle and fold over, and you have one less seam to sew.  Sew up all the sides except for the top to make a kind of bag.  If you&amp;rsquo;re extending an existing pocket, cut off or seam-rip the existing bottom seam, and attach your new bag to this raw edge (you probably want to put the pocket-inside sides together so the seam ends up on the outside of the pocket).  If you&amp;rsquo;re adding a new pocket, pick a seam where you want to attach your pocket and seam-rip it open.  Put the inside of the pocket-bag and the outside of the garment together, so that the seam ends up on the inside of the garment.  You can watch Morgan Donner do some very neat pockets with a sewing machine &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7pE_nrHKd58&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but the principle is basically the same for hand-sewing pockets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reattaching buttons: Video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Du6gq3ks0SQ&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Essentially, you sew it to the garment through the holes a bunch of times.  Reattaching a belt loop is much the same, except that belt loops do not have convenient holes in them and they&amp;rsquo;re like a billion layers thick.  I recommend getting a thimble, or using small pliers to push the needle through, if you&amp;rsquo;re reattaching a belt loop on jeans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hemming pants or sleeves:  If there&amp;rsquo;s not a complicated cuff or anything that you want to preserve, you can fold up the extra material on the inside of the pant, then stitch around the edge.  You can do a more complicated fold if you want to keep the original hem of, say, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P02Mne95-s8&#34;&gt;jeans&lt;/a&gt;.  Button-down shirt sleeves, however, are complex enough that you might consider using a professional alterations shop&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (or just wear it permanently cuffed &amp;ndash; a flannel shirt cuffed halfway between your wrists and elbows is a classic gay look).  Use a running stitch for non-stretch fabric, or a zigzag stitch (exactly what it says on the tin) for stretch fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you search YouTube for sewing tutorials, you&amp;rsquo;ll find that a lot of them use a sewing machine and press things after every step and stuff like that.  You don&amp;rsquo;t really need a sewing machine for basic repairs like the ones I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed in this post &amp;ndash; you can do the same seams by hand.  Pressing stuff will make it look neater, but it&amp;rsquo;s also really annoying (and you have to make sure to set the temperature correctly for your fabric type), so I typically don&amp;rsquo;t do it.  But I also never weave in the ends on anything I knit or crochet to the point where I&amp;rsquo;ll just wear a sweater everywhere with strings hanging off of it, so take that with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other, non-clothing things I&amp;rsquo;ve used my sewing skills for:  Repairing my roommate&amp;rsquo;s rocking chair (it&amp;rsquo;s a wooden frame with canvas stretched over it to form the seat and back, which tore).  Attaching a loop of string to my bath towel so it hangs on a hook better.  Embroidering my initials on a kitchen towel that I kept in my dorm&amp;rsquo;s communal kitchen.  Making little quilts (I don&amp;rsquo;t have the patience for a whole quilt, and these are admittedly less useful but they ARE cuter).  Adding a drawstring to a pride flag so I could use it as a curtain in my dorm room.  Making a weighted blanket (much cheaper than buying one would&amp;rsquo;ve been).  Fixing a pillow that had a blowout.  Attaching a cheap fleece blanket to a comfy chair with really itchy upholstery I got for free when Stata was replacing everyone&amp;rsquo;s desk chairs.  Attaching a nice edging to a cross-stitch where I stupidly went way too close to the edge of the aida so it was impossible to mount in a frame.  Making miscellaneous bags.  And, of course, finishing work on an untold number of knitting and crochet projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not already hip to the concept of clothing alterations, and my primary audience of engineers probably isn&amp;rsquo;t: Off-the-rack clothes don&amp;rsquo;t really fit anyone very well.  However, if you get something that fits you in key areas, a professional alterations person can cover up a multitude of other sins.  Clothes fitting in the general sense is out of scope for this post, but a few general rules are that shirts/jackets need to initially fit in the shoulders (armscyes are hell to modify), pants should fit in the butt and thighs but they&amp;rsquo;re easy to hem or take in at the waist, and extra fabric can be removed but more cannot be conjured.  Minor alterations can make a surprisingly large difference in how put-together you look, and they&amp;rsquo;re not that expensive, especially on a programmer salary.  I really can&amp;rsquo;t evangelize this enough. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Legibility and MIT&#39;s Mandatory Meal Plans</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/mealplan/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/mealplan/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 22-Aug-2020:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/tanyachen/nyu-uga-college-students-sharing-fyre-fest-quarantine-meals&#34;&gt;i fuckin&#39; called it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MIT&amp;rsquo;s policy for allowing students back on campus in the fall is upsetting a lot of students for a lot of reasons.  I won&amp;rsquo;t go into detail about most of these here, since I wanted to focus on one thing: the meal plan is now mandatory for all students who live in dorms, who are no longer permitted to use the kitchens.  And if you are an undergraduate not living in the dorms you are not allowed to access campus (yes, even if your apartment with its private kitchenette is a 5-minute walk from campus, and yes, even though the admins hinted strongly that space concerns were the main limitation preventing them from allowing more students back on campus, with the result that a lot of students have already signed leases for off-campus apartments).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Worth noting at this point: the main way COVID gets transmitted is droplets or airborne viruses, and surfaces are a lot less of a concern.  Using a dining hall means you have to: go to a poorly-ventilated place, hand a dining hall employee your ID so they can swipe it at the machine and you can breathe at each other, get in a line with a bunch of other people to get your food, potentially talk to the stir-fry chef if you&amp;rsquo;re in the stir-fry line, and either sit down at a table in a room with a bunch of other people to eat your food or put it in a takeout box and eat it in your room.  There are five dining halls, and probably at least 1000 students will be on campus in the fall; the dining halls can not &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; be configured so that only one student is in there at a time, never mind the dining employees!  Meanwhile, if there&amp;rsquo;s, say, 20 people to a kitchen in a cook-for-yourself dorm, you could reasonably create a sign-up sheet to make sure only two people, who both live on the same floor and use the same bathrooms, can be in the kitchen at a time at any given time.  Or only one person, if you&amp;rsquo;re very paranoid &amp;ndash; at 20 people per kitchen, you can give everyone one-hour evening slots a few times a week to cook a few meals&#39; worth of food, or 15-minute slots every morning and night to quickly fry something or use the microwave.  Or let people on the floor form pods, and relax social distancing measures within the pod, so that the pod can all be in the kitchen at the same time.  I&amp;rsquo;m a robotics engineer, Jim, not an epidemiologist, but I think it very well might be safer to have everyone in cook-for-yourself dorms use their floor kitchens, under some system where you minimize the number of people in the kitchen simultaneously.  But this is somewhat beside the point &amp;ndash; I want to discuss the implications of the current rules as they exist.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, Disability Services will help people who have life-threatening allergies or other dietary restrictions that affect their ability to eat dining hall food.  (I don&amp;rsquo;t know how exemptions for religious dietary restrictions work so I&amp;rsquo;m going to stick to discussing medical-related ones.)  This is already a thing they do on a regular basis.  If you have documentation from a medical professional, and if you contact their office and go through their vetting process, they will go to bat for you and help you to the best of their ability.  I love MIT Disability Services &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt;.  Most other campus disability services offices are in the business of providing the minimum possible legally mandated amount of help and dragging their feet about it so much that a student may as well just drop out unless they&amp;rsquo;re very determined and have some amount of legal clout on their side.  (MIT Mental Health is also astoundingly good &amp;ndash; just look at Stanford!  Their mental health department, &lt;a href=&#34;https://mv-voice.com/news/2019/10/08/in-historic-settlement-stanford-agrees-to-revise-leave-of-absence-policies-for-students-in-mental-health-crisis&#34;&gt;until they were sued out of doing it&lt;/a&gt;, systematically &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/28/us/college-suicide-stanford-leaves.html&#34;&gt;pushed depressed students to take leaves of absence&lt;/a&gt; so that when they commit suicide at least it&amp;rsquo;s not on campus so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make Stanford look bad.  But that&amp;rsquo;s another post for another time&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.)  I will sing the praises of SDS any day of the week.  (Did you know that if you have a temporary injury you should also talk to SDS and they&amp;rsquo;ll help you figure out how to access the stuff you need?  Did you know that if you&amp;rsquo;re e.g. trans and incredibly dysphoric about taking the swim test, SDS can help you get an alternative private swim test?  Even if it&amp;rsquo;s a problem you don&amp;rsquo;t think SDS can help with, I super recommend sending them an email and setting up a meeting.  They know a lot about MIT and they&amp;rsquo;re doing their best to help.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, when I first met with SDS about my auditory processing disorder as a freshman, I brought a file folder with eight separate things in it including reports from two different audiologists with lists of accommodations they recommended for me.  And they still couldn&amp;rsquo;t provide one of the accommodations I&amp;rsquo;d requested (it would&amp;rsquo;ve apparently represented an undue burden on professors to have to provide notes to me in advance of lecture so I could follow along; they do have a well-used mechanism in place for hiring other students to take notes for you and send them after class, but I declined it).  I probably didn&amp;rsquo;t need to provide quite this much documentation, but it&amp;rsquo;s safer if your disability is so rock-solidly documented there&amp;rsquo;s no room for them to deny it.  I don&amp;rsquo;t know if abled people, by and large, know how big an uphill fight it is to get the accommodations you need.  Even with people like SDS who are on your side and want to do their best for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what if&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you feel really gross after eating beef or eggplant or tomatoes but it&amp;rsquo;s not an allergy or anything you have documentation for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you&amp;rsquo;re autistic and arbitrarily hate the texture of a long list of foods?  (You will not be surprised to learn how many MIT students are autistic.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you&amp;rsquo;ve found experimentally that you feel much less constantly fatigued when you avoid gluten, but don&amp;rsquo;t have a diagnosis and can&amp;rsquo;t access a doctor that would back you up? (This is a common symptom of my not-very-rare chronic illness which is not well represented by the medical literature; my specialist told me about it because she&amp;rsquo;s very good at her job.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you&amp;rsquo;re allergic to enough stuff that you can eat one (1) meal from the dining hall, so you can&amp;rsquo;t technically &amp;ldquo;not eat any of the dining hall food&amp;rdquo;, and now you&amp;rsquo;re staring down the barrel of having to eat the same thing every single fucking day for an entire semester?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you&amp;rsquo;re a vegetarian and you&amp;rsquo;re allergic to eggplant, which MIT Dining for some reason really loves to put in the vegetarian option, so you can&amp;rsquo;t technically &amp;ldquo;not eat any of the dining hall food&amp;rdquo; because once in a blue moon the dining hall will have something you can eat and of course there&amp;rsquo;s always the salad bar, but in total this doesn&amp;rsquo;t get you anywhere near enough calories to live on?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you did an elimination diet yourself and figured out you were allergic to one of the 8 top allergens, but you can&amp;rsquo;t afford to go to the doctor to get an official diagnosis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you were diagnosed with lactose intolerance as a pretty young child but you no longer talk to your abusive family so you have no medical documentation to back this up, just the fun party trick of drinking a glass of milk and getting explosive diarrhea afterwards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/design_legibility/&#34;&gt;legibility&lt;/a&gt;, this sounds like another refrain of the same old song.  People who have dietary restrictions &lt;em&gt;that are legible to Disability Services&lt;/em&gt; can get accommodations&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  And the way you make things legible to Disability Services is to go through the medical system, with all its &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20200513162453/https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/04/24/employer-provided-health-insurance-delenda-est/&#34;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1540620.html&#34;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1279873.html&#34;&gt;varied&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1388220.html&#34;&gt;modes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://va.media.tumblr.com/tumblr_p07iu5P87s1qkj9tt_720.mp4&#34;&gt;of failure&lt;/a&gt;.  I believe that the fine people of MIT Disability Services will honestly do their best, under the circumstances, to help people who have undocumented or underdocumented or just plain weird dietary restrictions.  But that&amp;rsquo;s kind of a shaky guarantee!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, under normal circumstances, this is already a thing SDS deals with frequently.  This is because the current meal plan requires all freshmen in dorms with dining halls to be on the meal plan.  Under normal circumstances, if you can&amp;rsquo;t get this exemption and you want to cook for yourself anyway, you can go live in one of the cook-for-yourself dorms.  &lt;em&gt;Right now&lt;/em&gt;, if you really need an exemption and can&amp;rsquo;t get one, you&amp;rsquo;re completely and totally fucked, because you have to be on the meal plan to live in ANY dorm, and you have to live in a dorm (FSILGs not included) to access campus.  If you urgently need physical campus access for your senior capstone project, or an important lab class that will throw off your whole plan to graduate if postponed, or your UROP project that will get you into grad school, well, uh, better figure out a way to cope with MIT Dining poisoning you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or get your food from somewhere else &amp;ndash; but you&amp;rsquo;ll still be required to &lt;em&gt;pay&lt;/em&gt; for a 14-meal-a-week meal plan (most of the dining halls serve breakfast and dinner).  Oh, yes, the meal plan is discounted!  The meal plan is discounted, because we care &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; about low-income students.  It&amp;rsquo;s discounted by 40%, so you&amp;rsquo;ll only have to pay 60% of the normal sticker price.  For 14 meals a week, assuming 15 weeks a semester, the discounted meal plan costs $9/meal; my friend who meal-preps tells me you can cook-for-yourself for about $2/meal, so already this is going to cause problems for some number of students who don&amp;rsquo;t even have any of the ~problematic~ dietary restrictions I&amp;rsquo;m focusing on here.  (Theoretically, financial aid, if you get a financial aid package with a dining allowance, will pay for the meal plan plus a little extra so you can buy yourself some lunches on campus.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s say you&amp;rsquo;re a student and you really need campus access and you can&amp;rsquo;t live with the consequences (figuratively or literally) of eating dining-hall food but you also can&amp;rsquo;t get an exemption.  You will still have to pay for your unused, discounted mealplan, and since you can&amp;rsquo;t use the kitchens unless you have Special Permission (for example to make a birthday cake!  As if the dorm communities that make each other birthday cakes are surviving this intact!  So you can get poisoned on a daily basis by dining, but at least you and your friends, assuming any of your friends are on campus, can have a nice little socially distanced birthday party in a kitchen that has been carefully disinfected before and after!) &amp;ndash; as I was saying, since you can&amp;rsquo;t use the kitchens without Special Permission, your actual food source will have to be something like the Chipotle Meal Plan, which gets very expensive very fast.  Or perhaps you will illegally keep a microwave and an electric teapot and an Instant Pot in your room and survive on whatever eldritch concoctions you can make that way.  Or maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll pick the lock on the kitchen door so that you can secretly scramble yourself a plate of eggs every morning.  While, of course, paying for the food you can&amp;rsquo;t eat &amp;ndash; the stuff that, tauntingly, looks like food and smells like food, but isn&amp;rsquo;t food &lt;em&gt;to you&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; from the discounted mealplan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the comforting knowledge that the only thing MIT has to say to students like you is: &lt;strong&gt;let them eat cake&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19.mit.edu/fall-2020-faq&#34;&gt;MIT Fall 2020 FAQ&lt;/a&gt;, particularly the section &amp;ldquo;Will cook-for-yourself undergraduate communities have everyday access to kitchens?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case Rafael Reif is actually reading this &amp;ndash; whenever you&amp;rsquo;re making an announcement like this, you &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to include as one of the FAQs a detailed description of your appeal process for dealing with exemption requests that aren&amp;rsquo;t legible to any other part of the system.  You need to say explicitly what documentation you want to see, if any, and under what circumstances you would waive the requirement for documentation.  Preferably you should also give a few examples of exemptions you would give and exemptions you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t give.  I know you hate this.  I know you want to be vague about it so you can do things on a case-by-case basis and exercise your professional judgment&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and maintain as much flexibility as possible.  But I need you to understand: for us as students who need to plan, a vague &amp;ldquo;maybe&amp;rdquo; is the same as a no.  Have enough courage and kindness to tell us where the line is, and enough humility to admit that you can&amp;rsquo;t lay down any kind of law without someone getting caught in an edge case so you&amp;rsquo;d better have a good process for dealing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t done this because you didn&amp;rsquo;t realize you&amp;rsquo;d need a robust appeal process, or you haven&amp;rsquo;t considered how to design it at all &amp;ndash; to me, that&amp;rsquo;s a fireable, unforgivable offense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Hey, look, guys, I finally figured out Markdown footnotes!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, turns out I&amp;rsquo;m not quite done.  Schools like MIT and Caltech have a reputation for being very difficult and very stressful and having a high suicide rate.  While it&amp;rsquo;s true that MIT is pretty stressful, for undergrads we also have institutions like Student Support Services and Student Disability Services, and mental health from MIT Medical is free.  Many students take leaves of absence when necessary and the administration has put in some effort into making sure the process of returning from the leave goes reasonably smoothly.  Unfortunately, I think grad students are a bit more hung out to dry &amp;ndash; but I&amp;rsquo;m not [quite] one so I can&amp;rsquo;t really testify.  Also, if your mental health issues are related to being LGBT+, MIT Medical is really quite good on trans healthcare, and many dorms/living communities have high LGBT+ populations.  I don&amp;rsquo;t think mental health in general is super high on anyone&amp;rsquo;s radar when they&amp;rsquo;re choosing colleges, but I think it should be &amp;ndash; and I think on this axis MIT does really well.  If you&amp;rsquo;d like to talk to me personally about anything related to mental health or disability services at MIT, I&amp;rsquo;d be delighted to expand more on this over email. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I am going to write a post about invisible disabilities and legibility and the concept of &amp;ldquo;faking it&amp;rdquo;.  This was going to be that post, but it turns out I had other things to say. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a joke, referring to every major campus issue that&amp;rsquo;s happened over the past four years but especially to the way MIT handled exemption requests to the March move of kicking everyone off campus.  One of my hallmates had no family outside of China and MIT&amp;rsquo;s response was to ask her to &amp;ldquo;get creative&amp;rdquo; and consider sleeping on a friend&amp;rsquo;s couch.  For the rest of the semester.  While still somehow getting enough coursework done to graduate. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Living with Chronic Fatigue</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/fatigue/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/fatigue/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was diagnosed with my chronic illness (being a bit vague for the sake of privacy) in the fall of 2015.  I&amp;rsquo;m still not great at coping with it, but I have learned some things.  To some extent, this post is what I wish I&amp;rsquo;d told my past self five years ago &amp;ndash; except that I&amp;rsquo;m not sure my past self would&amp;rsquo;ve listened.  To some extent I wrote this for myself in order to process my feelings.  If any of this is ever useful to anyone who isn&amp;rsquo;t me, I&amp;rsquo;ll be delighted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;normal-isnt-coming-back&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Normal&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t coming back&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some part of me was, and continues to be, convinced that if I can just perfectly calibrate my medication then I can continue to do all the same dumb shit I used to do and have as much energy as I used to have.  Spoiler alert: no.  Even properly medicated, I&amp;rsquo;m still kind of tired a lot of the time, and I&amp;rsquo;m never going to have quite as much energy as I feel like I &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; have.  I did also have to make some lifestyle changes: I can no longer eat soy or gluten, since the former does long-term damage to my body and the latter makes me tired as all hell.  Also, (shockingly!) having a regular bedtime and getting adequate sleep has helped a lot (unfortunately, I go to MIT and I have a horrible tendency to procrastinate and then pull all-nighters&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, you know what, even the oft-doctor-touted lifestyle changes won&amp;rsquo;t fix everything.  I&amp;rsquo;m always going to be chronically fatigued.  I keep burning out because I try to push myself past my limits (see: that one semester when I tried to take five classes plus a UROP plus two of the classes are grad classes so they&amp;rsquo;re on the schedule where they give you no homework one week and then send you to hell the next; also see: how I got my knee injury).  MIT has a lot of demigods who can, seemingly effortlessly, keep on top of a crushing workload.  That&amp;rsquo;s never going to be me, for several reasons &amp;ndash; but one of them is that I just don&amp;rsquo;t have that many hours in the day where I have enough energy to do stuff.  And that is incredibly and endlessly frustrating to me!!  I want to do stuff!  Desperately, agonizingly, I want to make things and build things, but I have remarkably little time to do it in because I spend so much of my time sitting around doing &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; because I literally don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy to do anything else.  And that&amp;rsquo;s not going to change.  Picturing a godlike being of pure productivity when I make my to-do lists doesn&amp;rsquo;t make me any less of a lump.  The only thing I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do is plan very carefully so I can try to use my limited energy to the best of my ability.  Although this sounds kind of stupid and obvious as I write it, it truly has been the hardest thing for me to accept.  There&amp;rsquo;s no sneaky way for me to become more than I am.  I am always going to be chronically fatigued, and I will have to make the best of that, and make peace with the knowledge that I will die unsatisfied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man&amp;rsquo;s reach must exceed his grasp, or what&amp;rsquo;s a heaven for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Edited to add: Some things I&amp;rsquo;ve read that I have found helpful for thinking about this include &lt;a href=&#34;https://thingofthings.wordpress.com/2018/07/19/on-laziness/&#34;&gt;thingofthings&#39; On Laziness&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://theunitofcaring.tumblr.com/tagged/executive-dysfunction&#34;&gt;theunitofcaring&amp;rsquo;s executive dysfunction tag&lt;/a&gt;.  Although ADHD and depression are not the same thing as fatigue, all of them affect your ability to Do Things in a way that you largely can&amp;rsquo;t overcome by adding Willpower.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, that one was depressing.  I promise the rest of these are real tips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pay-attention-to-your-body-and-limits&#34;&gt;Pay attention to your body and limits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very bad at paying attention to stuff that&amp;rsquo;s going on with my body, to the point where I&amp;rsquo;ve configured my computer to send me a push notification every hour reminding me to check if I have a headache.  Unfortunately, while this skill is important for everyone, it&amp;rsquo;s way more important if you have chronic fatigue.  In the evenings, I often won&amp;rsquo;t notice that I&amp;rsquo;ve run out of energy until I&amp;rsquo;ve, uh, run out of energy, at which point I no longer have enough energy to go to bed.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t a problem I&amp;rsquo;ve totally solved yet, but some things help with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a regular bedtime so that my fatigue level as a function of time-of-day is relatively predictable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set an alarm a couple hours before bedtime to do pre-bed activities, like putting on pajamas and brushing teeth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have my roommates drag me out of my comfy chair in our living room where I&amp;rsquo;m trying my very best to fall asleep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not, do not, do not say of any task that &amp;ldquo;I have to do this before I go to bed today&amp;rdquo;, because that&amp;rsquo;s how I end up reading Hacker News on my phone until 4am in a futile attempt to force myself to take a shower.  If it hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened before 10pm, it ain&amp;rsquo;t happening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My medication is a fucking lifesaver, but it also makes me overheat very easily.  I reach peak functionality in a very narrow temperature range, and if it gets too warm, my energy just melts away.  (I used to take a lot of pride in how well I could withstand hot temperatures, but in hindsight it&amp;rsquo;s not clear to what extent this was an untreated symptom of my illness.)  I keep a CO2 monitor with an internal thermometer in my room, so that at least I&amp;rsquo;m fully informed when I need to make the tradeoff between closing the window so the A/C can keep up and opening it so my room gets below 1000 PPM CO2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More seriously, I also have a hard time realizing when I need to tweak my meds.  You&amp;rsquo;d think it&amp;rsquo;d be easy to notice that gradually over a period of a few weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve started sleeping 10-11 hours a night, spending the day slouching in various chairs aimlessly browsing the Internet, and getting grouchy/depressed on a hair trigger.  Especially since I theoretically &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; that I always need to tweak my dose around halfway through a semester because of the changing seasons.  Unfortunately, you&amp;rsquo;d be wrong &amp;ndash; my internal experience just feels normal.  Since the shift happens so gradually, it&amp;rsquo;s kind of a boiling frog situation.  This leads me to my next point&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;collect-data-on-important-metrics-and-pay-attention-to-it&#34;&gt;Collect data on important metrics, and pay attention to it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important metrics for tracking my particular illness are resting heart rate, average hours of sleep per night, subjective fatigue level, and subjective mood.  To solve the first two, I got a Fitbit a few years ago, and it&amp;rsquo;s one of the most impactful decisions I&amp;rsquo;ve ever made about managing my chronic illness (the other one was &amp;ldquo;let me try quitting gluten for a month to see if it helps&amp;rdquo;).  The last two are less solved, because I kind of definitionally have to spend some time at the end of the day recording my subjective fatigue level somewhere, and as I&amp;rsquo;ve explained, any task that I have to do right before bed every day is going to be first against the wall whenever the delicate systems keeping me functional get slightly out of whack.  But to the extent that I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to maintain that habit, it&amp;rsquo;s been helpful.  I&amp;rsquo;ve also told my roommates to keep an eye out if I seem more lethargic than usual, and to some extent I can look back on my to-do list for the week, compare the ratio of completed tasks to postponed tasks, and take a wild fucking guess as to why that ratio seems kinda low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of those things that probably seems stupid or obvious or dead-simple before you&amp;rsquo;ve repeatedly had the experience of [being horribly behind on psets, skipping all social events and still not getting ahead, sleeping so much you keep sleeping through commitments so now all your friends think you&amp;rsquo;re a flake, etc. for the past month] and suddenly realizing OH FUCK I KNOW WHAT&amp;rsquo;S GOING ON THERE I NEED TO EMAIL MY DOCTOR.  Learn from my mistakes.  Figure out your important metrics, figure out how to track them, and check up on them once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-your-ingenuity-to-route-around-obstacles&#34;&gt;Use your ingenuity to route around obstacles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other day, I suggested to my roommates that we put in a conveyor belt for transporting empty tea mugs from my room into the kitchen &amp;ndash; or, barring this, a robot that I could summon to carry them.  These particular suggestions were vetoed, but I think the mindset is important.  I don&amp;rsquo;t want to waste my precious, limited energy on doing stupid shit like &lt;em&gt;carrying mugs around&lt;/em&gt; (and remembering that the mugs exist and setting up meta-systems so I remember to take care of the mugs, at some time when I have the energy for it, before I run out of clean tea infusers).  I want to save it for the stuff that matters, which I can do precisely to the extent that I can leverage my engineering skills to make basic life tasks go away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to forget to drink water and get dehydrated, so I collected a bunch of water bottles from career fair that I keep filled in a bag by my desk.  Music helps give me energy and keep me focused, so I have an elaborate system of playlists for every occasion (now what I need is for my Fitbit to be able to automatically trigger one when I fall asleep at the wrong time).  I have ten identical boxes of microwave enchiladas lined up in the freezer, and I eat one for lunch every day, because they take like no effort to cook and I&amp;rsquo;ll always find them appetizing enough to eat, so I also don&amp;rsquo;t have to spend any cycles deciding on a lunch.  I keep my meds and a leakproof water bottle in a three-compartment pencil cup that&amp;rsquo;s attached to my bedframe by a C-clamp, so I can swallow my meds as soon as I&amp;rsquo;m half-awake enough to realize my alarm is going off.  More generally, organization of my desk and my room more broadly is super important to me, because I want it to be falling-off-a-log easy to put stuff away right after I use it (because then I don&amp;rsquo;t have to spend as much time on a weekly/monthly basis organizing).  I could go on about the many, many things I do in very specific ways for very specific reasons, but I think I&amp;rsquo;ve gone on long enough.  It&amp;rsquo;s worthwhile to spend some energy upfront putting these systems and habits in place so that future me can save it for more interesting activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;dont-waste-energy-on-your-infrastructure&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t waste energy on your infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is kind of the inverse of the last point, but I want to illustrate it with a story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom has a set of family-heirloom antique bedroom furniture, consisting of a vanity and a chest of drawers.  The drawers don&amp;rsquo;t have glides; they simply slide in their slots, and frequently this motion is less of a gentle slide and more of a desperate jerk because humidity has caused one component or another to swell up.  (And this is in California.)  When I was a kid, for some reason my parents decided that I should have this furniture in my room&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  I couldn&amp;rsquo;t physically pull open many of the drawers, and others were too tall for me to see into.  Unsurprisingly, if anything I needed to access frequently was stored in these drawers, pretty soon it would instead be stored all over my floor.  I spent years and years just coping with this by letting my mom store my least-frequently-accessed items in them.  Finally, when I was about fifteen, I realized that, although this was the way things had always been, it was not the way things &lt;em&gt;had to be&lt;/em&gt;; furthermore, I did not &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; this situation, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to live like that anymore.  So I traded the antique furniture for one of my parents&#39; chests of drawers and an additional drawer unit from Ikea, and now it lives in my parents&#39; bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of your routines, accreted over your years of existence, may be something like this.  You may be doing things because it&amp;rsquo;s the way your parents told you to do them, or because you got into the habit a long time ago when it was actually adaptive to your environment, or because you read a blog post about it, or just because.  I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you: you don&amp;rsquo;t have to live like that anymore.  Be ruthless in cutting the crap.  If you can spend a small amount of money on a problem that makes it go away and never bother you again, do that.  (This is why there are minimum two trash cans in every room of my house.)  Inspect all your routines, particularly the ones you don&amp;rsquo;t think too much about anymore.  Think about the way your stuff is organized and the way you use it &amp;ndash; is there any way you can do a one-time reorganization that permanently reduces the number of steps in some task?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that aesthetics are often the cause of inefficiency in my personal routines.  I have never particularly been infected with the notion that my home needs to be Pinterest-perfect in order for me to invite company over, but if you are: your friends want to see you, and they probably don&amp;rsquo;t really care about the state of your house.  If they do, get better friends.  I like looking at fancy bullet journals on social media, but my planner is always going to be a mess, because I need to be able to scribble stuff down in it &lt;em&gt;right now before I forget&lt;/em&gt;, and if I have to think about handwriting or highlighter colors at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; in order to use my planner, eventually my to-do list will end up on sticky notes stuck to my monitor (or, worse, totally forgotten).  I&amp;rsquo;m all about messy-but-it-works-for-me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Not, of course, to be confused with messy-and-I-pretend-it-works-but-it-kinda-doesn&amp;rsquo;t.  Or with so-messy-it&amp;rsquo;s-distracting.  I care about the aesthetics of the spaces that I live and work in &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; to the extent that those aesthetics make my spaces more pleasing and functional.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;consider-mobility-aids-and-other-physical-accommodations&#34;&gt;Consider mobility aids (and other physical accommodations)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe a wheelchair (manual or powered) or a cane or a walker will make it easier for you to do the stuff that matters to you!  Or maybe the mobility aid you want is not one of the classic medical ones, but a scooter or electric bike or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/pHhRt2q3K6KfFE5kd/nyoom&#34;&gt;something else of that nature&lt;/a&gt;.  Maybe you need to get a tall stool so that you can sit down in the kitchen while you cook.  Maybe you want a &lt;a href=&#34;https://comp-lady.tumblr.com/post/182341622121/glorious-spoon-theunitofcaring-i-dont-get&#34;&gt;shower chair&lt;/a&gt;.  Maybe you want a rolling cart (with the nice trefoil wheels so it can go up stairs) so you can carry your groceries home without feeling completely wiped afterwards.  Personally, I really want to build a big hexapod robot with a chair on it that I can drive around MIT when I&amp;rsquo;m going to classes on bad knee days (part of the reason for the legs is for stairs, but mostly I just want to skitter about like a large, horrible insect).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to think something along the lines of &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;well, I don&amp;rsquo;t need any of those, I&amp;rsquo;m not &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; disabled&amp;rdquo;.  That&amp;rsquo;s internalized ableism, baby!  Energy is a precious resource, and anything that can help you save it for the stuff that matters is worth trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sheer-productivity-is-not-the-ultimate-measure-of-a-human-being&#34;&gt;Sheer productivity is not the ultimate measure of a human being&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too often, I tend to judge myself by grades and productivity and stuff I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt;, and of course by these standards I can always be found wanting.  But there&amp;rsquo;s much more to life!  Sitting and thinking, relaxing, admiring the view, smelling the roses&amp;hellip; even if I&amp;rsquo;m short of energy for everything else in life, I still have art and beauty.  I believe I am worth more &amp;ndash; that we all, by simple virtue of being humans, are worth more &amp;ndash; than the &amp;ldquo;productive work&amp;rdquo; that can be extracted from our bodies and minds.  I have found that, to the extent that I can internalize this, I am happier.  Maybe this mindset can help you, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;codas-for-the-abled-mostly-unrelated-to-each-other&#34;&gt;Codas for the abled, mostly unrelated to each other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We disabled people have invented various metaphors to describe what it&amp;rsquo;s like to have a limited reserve of a precious resource that you need to manage because you can&amp;rsquo;t Do Stuff when it&amp;rsquo;s exhausted (and, yes, getting dressed and cooking food and basic hygiene count as Doing Stuff, even if &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; never think about them that way).  Most famous of these is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://butyoudontlooksick.com/articles/written-by-christine/the-spoon-theory/&#34;&gt;Spoon Theory&lt;/a&gt;, but we also have the &lt;a href=&#34;https://thingofthings.wordpress.com/2014/11/01/the-forks-model-of-disability/&#34;&gt;Forks Model&lt;/a&gt;, a different &lt;a href=&#34;https://jenroses.tumblr.com/post/181045322711/have-i-told-yall-about-my-husbands-fork-theory&#34;&gt;Fork Theory&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bittersnurr.tumblr.com/post/136161231597&#34;&gt;Battery Theory&lt;/a&gt;.  (There is also &amp;ldquo;Knife Theory&amp;rdquo;, which is what you use when you are out of spoons and some well-meaning abled person tells you to do yoga about it.)  I&amp;rsquo;ve glossed spoons as &amp;ldquo;energy&amp;rdquo; in this post, but it can have multiple meanings &amp;ndash; perhaps after some threshold of physical activity you&amp;rsquo;re in too much pain to continue, or you run the risk of permanently (further) damaging your body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple minutes ago I read about the related concept of &lt;a href=&#34;http://globalprioritiesproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/NeutralHours.pdf&#34;&gt;neutral hours&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2015/03/17/carpe-diem-the-optimization-game-level-1/&#34;&gt;three-resource model of Doing Stuff&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; the resources being Time, Money, and Energy.  I like it as a formalization but I think it could be improved by the addition of probabilistic reasoning (if you are programming, your estimate of what you&amp;rsquo;ll accomplish in a specific hour is subject to some amount of randomness, for example if you run into an unexpected bug; if you are doing a recuperation activity, it has some risk of failing to actually recover your energy &amp;ndash; see the Forks Model above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My chronic illness is an autoimmune disorder, and while I&amp;rsquo;m not per se immunocompromised, my immune system still behaves in weird ways.  One time I caught a cold that was going around campus that caused fairly mild symptoms in everyone else &amp;ndash; while I had all the same cold symptoms, I was also so fatigued that I spent three days in bed.  I can&amp;rsquo;t totally pin this on my chronic illness since I was also very stressed and sleep-deprived due to final projects, but this experience is part of what&amp;rsquo;s informing my very paranoid approach to COVID.  I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to die yet, and the last thing I need is more chronic health issues; please wear a mask, and keep your distance if you see me on the street.  (You&amp;rsquo;ll recognize me because my face mask is made of fabric printed with blue and purple cats.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first got my diagnosis, multiple people expressed their condolences.  To me, this seems like entirely the wrong sentiment.  It&amp;rsquo;s as if they think that the diagnosis &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; the illness: no, I was already sick!  It&amp;rsquo;s just that now I know what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with me, so I can start fixing it!  The software engineer&amp;rsquo;s analogy to a diagnosis might be finally figuring out the cause for a subtle bug, maybe involving concurrency or something gnarly like that.  Also, for many chronically ill people, getting diagnosed is an uphill fight through a long series of doctors who think you&amp;rsquo;re faking it or drug-seeking, and it&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon for this to take 5-10 years.  I got lucky here in that I only really had to suffer the untreated side-effects of my illness for around a year.  In my case, these side-effects were depression and extreme fatigue as my body slowly shut down with me in it, and (inconveniently) they reached their peak during my senior year of high school.  I don&amp;rsquo;t want to dwell too much on that wretched experience, except to note that getting diagnosed and medicated was nothing short of miraculous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t relevant, but who am I to turn down the opportunity to tell you about the worst all-nighter of my college career?  I&amp;rsquo;d actually pulled two back-to-back all-nighters because I had to finish a very long paper about Thelonious Monk for my jazz class and also I think a nasty controls pset where Matlab had done its level best to send me to hell, so during the preceding 72 hours I&amp;rsquo;d gotten maybe 6 total hours of catnaps in.  After putting a bow on my paper I was mostly oriented well enough to stumble to class and attempt to write notes; unfortunately, the first class of the day was in fact my jazz class, where we spent the whole period listening to incomprehensible free jazz and I drifted in and out of lucidity and consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(If you are unacquainted with free jazz, please go look some up on Youtube, and play it as you read the rest of this story for atmosphere.  If you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; acquainted with free jazz and are &lt;em&gt;vibrating&lt;/em&gt; with the urge to explain to me how I Just Don&amp;rsquo;t Get It, please contain yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My handwriting always gets dramatically less legible when I&amp;rsquo;m sleep-deprived, but even without that factor, my notes from this class period were fully incomprehensible because some guy with a saxophone was doing his level best to eject me to another plane of reality.  Normally I took 3-5 pages of notes in jazz class.  My notes from this date are limited to one page, where I dutifully copied down the timeline the professor wrote on the whiteboard and wrote disjointed words next to it, devoid of context or reason.  &amp;ldquo;Commodity&amp;rdquo; is in quotes in the middle of the page, with no obvious physical or contextual relationship to anything whatsoever.  I&amp;rsquo;ve never been on acid, but if it&amp;rsquo;s anything like not sleeping for 72 hours and then spending an hour trying to remain awake at all costs while listening to free jazz, I would prefer not to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I was released, blinking, into the rare sunlight shining down on Killian Court, with just enough time to grab an unsatisfying sushi lunch from the stud[ent center] before my controls class.  No notes from this class were ever uploaded to the course website, so I was normally pretty religious about going to it, but I decided after some introspection that I had better book it back to my dorm room for a nap instead before I fully passed out.  In the end I barely made it through the door, dropped my backpack uncaringly on the floor, and collapsed onto my bed fully clothed, with my feet in their boots sticking off the side because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the energy to kick them off (the boots, that is; not the feet).  The nap was, indeed, delicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do this. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, I never even significantly damaged the furniture.  There&amp;rsquo;s a water stain in the shape of a hair clip that was inflicted by my mom&amp;rsquo;s younger sister, and a light spot in the shape of a bottle cap due to the contractor who redid our bathrooms when I was about nine, but nothing from me.  I don&amp;rsquo;t think most children are like this &amp;ndash; and I certainly damaged plenty of other furniture (mostly desks, by scratching doodles into them).  For multiple reasons, I can&amp;rsquo;t recommend giving your child antique furniture. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Handle Detector</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/handle_detector/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/handle_detector/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last fall, I took &lt;a href=&#34;http://manipulation.csail.mit.edu/Fall2019/&#34;&gt;6.881 Intelligent Robot Manipulation&lt;/a&gt; (well, actually 6.881 is a &amp;ldquo;Special Subjects&amp;rdquo; course number, and when this course is offered again it&amp;rsquo;ll probably be renumbered, but that was the number I took it under).  We spent a lot of time on perception, because the first step in a manipulation problem is figuring out what the hell you&amp;rsquo;re looking at and where to grab it.  Often, you may want to grab something by the handle, which means you need to identify where the handle is on the object, which is where my final project comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a segmented object point cloud (a point cloud with just the object, and no table or other clutter that may be in the environment), I fitted &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quadric&#34;&gt;quadrics&lt;/a&gt; to randomly selected regions of the object, then used some simple heuristics to decide if the quadric probably represented a handle.  I used a recent algorithm for approximate quadric fitting that makes use of the object&amp;rsquo;s surface normals, so the actual quadric fitting step is very fast, at the price of needing to take the time to find surface normals (which a real perception pipeline will likely need anyway for other stuff).  I tested it on some objects with handles from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ycbbenchmarks.com/object-set/&#34;&gt;YCB object dataset&lt;/a&gt; and it works okay.  It didn&amp;rsquo;t do great on the mug and drill objects (which both have cylindrical areas that aren&amp;rsquo;t handles and non-quadric-shaped handles), but did pretty well on simple objects with cylindrical or ellipsoidal handles, even when I added noise to the point clouds.  Also, no machines were learned in the making of this project (I get the impression that ML would be the more &amp;ldquo;typical&amp;rdquo; way to do handle detection these days, but that has all the pitfalls of, uh, ML).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more, the paper I wrote about this project is 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/handle_detector/6881_paper.pdf&#34;&gt;here,&lt;/a&gt;
 and it has all my math, citations, test results, and pretty pictures.  Go look at the pretty pictures!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full course materials for 6.881 from Fall 2019 are available online &lt;a href=&#34;http://manipulation.csail.mit.edu/Fall2019/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and the currently-in-progress notes are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://manipulation.csail.mit.edu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  Prof. Tedrake also teaches the excellent 6.832 Underactuated Robotics, and his notes for that class are online &lt;a href=&#34;http://underactuated.csail.mit.edu/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  If you&amp;rsquo;re interested at all in either of these topics, I strongly recommend you read his notes!  They&amp;rsquo;re really good!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>You Are Not Immune To Amigurumi Crab</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/amigurumi-crab/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/amigurumi-crab/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/you_are_not_immune_to_crab.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;crab image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/amigurumi-crab&#34;&gt;This free crochet pattern&lt;/a&gt; for an amigurumi crab is one of the cutest little guys I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen.  His little face is a delight!  So, of course, I&amp;rsquo;ve made three of them (one for me and two as gifts).  You&amp;rsquo;ll need red (or other crab color) yarn, black yarn or embroidery floss for the smile, stuffing/fiberfill, and safety eyes (or you can just embroider your own eyes).  A tapestry needle will help with the joins, although you could do it all with just a crochet hook if stranded on a desert island.  Stitch markers help with following the pattern increases but aren&amp;rsquo;t strictly necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually I hate following patterns precisely, and typically make my own modifications; this crab is no exception.  Instead of real pincers, the original pattern just gives him vague club-like things &amp;ndash; which, like, c&amp;rsquo;mon, let him grab stuff!  So here&amp;rsquo;s my pattern for the pincer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big claw:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 sc in magic loop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 sc around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 sc in each of first 2 sc, sc in last 4 sc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 sc around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sc in first sc, 2 sc in each of next 2 sc, sc in last 5 sc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 sc around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sc in first 2 sc, sc2tog, sc in last 6 sc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sc in first sc, sc2tog, sc in last 5 sc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Break yarn &amp;amp; tie off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small claw:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same as big claw, but skip steps 5-7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sew together the two claws using the two stitches on each claw opposite the increases/decreases.  Stuff both claws, then SC around the 8 outside stitches (that is, excluding the two stitches from each claw that you&amp;rsquo;ve sewn together, but picking up all the other stitches around the outsides of the two claws) for five rounds.  Stuff, tuck all ends inside the claw, and attach to body as written in pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Let me know if this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense; I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually thought to take any pictures during this process.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go forth, and make yourself an excellent lil crab fren with the best lil smile!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Headphone Hooks</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/headphone_hooks/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/headphone_hooks/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I did not set out in life to be an audiophile, but at some point in life you look around and realize that you&amp;rsquo;ve spent hundreds of dollars on headphones and developed strong opinions on their quality, and at that point it seems kind of silly to deny that you&amp;rsquo;re an audophile.  So.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have three main sets of headphones that I keep at my desk: Sennheiser HD 280 Pro, Bose QC35 ii, and Sennheiser HD 6XX (Massdrop edition).  These all have different characteristics and serve different purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the HD 280s are wired headphones* with very good passive sound attenuation, and I&amp;rsquo;ve owned them for long enough that the original headband pad completely shredded, so it&amp;rsquo;s been replaced with a crochet pad I made.  The earpads are also coming unglued but I&amp;rsquo;m procrastinating on replacing them.  These were my daily driver headphones for walking around campus and doing work at my desk when my dorm was loud, which was a lot of the time (my dorm had other social properties that I liked enough for the noise to be worthwhile).  They clamp tightly to my head in such a way that I get headaches from prolonged use; glasses choice matters a lot for this (my current computer glasses frames were carefully selected to be as comfortable as possible for wearing headphones).  This tight clamping gives them better isolation properties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Bose headphones are wireless noise-canceling headphones.  I wear these when there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of environmental noise and the HD 280s don&amp;rsquo;t quite cut it.  I don&amp;rsquo;t like to wear wireless headphones when I can avoid it, but admittedly they are a lot better for walking around campus with (the HD 280s have this incredibly long and inconvenient cable and I developed a habit of spinning it around, which was probably dangerous/annoying for other hallway users).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the HD 6XX are my most recent headphone purchase, because I realized I had like $60 in Massdrop credits due to delayed keycap sets** and wanted to get myself a nice graduation/birthday present.  They are open-back headphones, because my new apartment is generally pretty quiet, and this bothers me less than noise canceling/attenuation for prolonged periods of time.  It&amp;rsquo;s also nice to be able to hear my roommates when they&amp;rsquo;re yelling for me.  These are my new daily driver headphones for doing work.  Open-back headphones also theoretically sound nicer/more &amp;ldquo;open&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I only have the one set of ears, so the headphones not in use have to go &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt;.  Previously, I was keeping all of these headphones piled up on a table near my desk.  This was annoying, and made it hard to put other things on the table; they&amp;rsquo;d also always end up on top of other items I keep on that table, like my stapler and tape dispenser.  Since headphones are sort of a funky shape, the common solution to the problem of headphone storage is the headphone hook, which is typically a cheap plastic hook with a sticky backing that you glue onto your desk somewhere.  I had a headphone hook stuck to my desk in my old dorm room, and it was ugly and felt a bit flimsy, especially since I kept piling multiple sets of headphones onto it.  Due to the furniture geometry, it also got in the way when I was moving out and had to pull my bookshelf away from the wall to rescue some stuff that fell behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, my new headphone hook solution was to buy three foldable wall-mount aluminum clothes hooks and a roll of double-sided VHB tape.  The set of three hooks cost ~$10 and the tape roll was 16ft for ~$20.  Of course, I didn&amp;rsquo;t use anywhere near the whole roll; I have practically the whole thing left for future endeavors to perma-stick things to other things.  In my new room geometry, there are no pieces of furniture being blocked by these hooks, but they&amp;rsquo;re foldable anyway so I can easily get them out of the way if that changes.  The hooks are stuck to the side of my loft bed ladder in a visually pleasing vertical line, which makes them all easy to access.  They&amp;rsquo;re also close enough to my laptop that I can leave the headphones plugged in while hanging them on the hook and the cable doesn&amp;rsquo;t get in the way of anything else.  I&amp;rsquo;m very pleased with this solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/headphone_hooks.png&#34; alt=&#34;headphone hooks, folded and unfolded, and with headphones hanging from them&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wrote the first draft of this post on Jun 8.  I&amp;rsquo;ve been using these hooks for a good few weeks now, and they&amp;rsquo;re great.  Unfortunately, this didn&amp;rsquo;t solve the perpetual-table-clutter problem, but at least the clutter is made of other stuff now &amp;ndash; progress?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* I am never sure how to deal with plural &amp;ldquo;headphones&amp;rdquo; grammatically.  the HD 280s are?  the HD 280 is a headphones?  the HD 280 is a headphone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;** Group-buy keycap sets are inevitably delayed.  Massdrop being an experienced group-buy manager, sometimes they do in fact deliver things on time, but I am a big fan of SA profile keycaps, and the SA production line has been very backed up lately.  And Massdrop gives me a $10 credit every time.  &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;:)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Robot Is A Sweet Boy, Doing His Best</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/robot_friend_01/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/robot_friend_01/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I see so many videos on social media of robots (usually from Boston Dynamics), with a flood of comments along the lines of &amp;ldquo;haha wow can&amp;rsquo;t wait for this thing to kill us all&amp;rdquo;.  Let me bust some myths: robots are like, kind of crap, you guys.  We&amp;rsquo;ve made a lot of amazing advances in controls for legged robots lately, particularly four-legged robots, and deep learning has vastly changed robot perception &amp;ndash; but stuff like object manipulation still sucks.  And most robot tasks, uh, kind of require object manipulation.  Boston Dynamics&#39; specialization is in controls, so if you want those robots to do high-level task and motion planning (of the kind you&amp;rsquo;d need to carry out a &amp;ldquo;kill all humans&amp;rdquo; order, or carry an object into a different room and set it gently on a table, or other extremely hard tasks like that) you&amp;rsquo;ll need to implement it yourself.  Also, most videos of robots doing stuff are carefully edited to include only the &lt;em&gt;successful&lt;/em&gt; runs; most likely either there&amp;rsquo;s 3x as much blooper reel footage that you don&amp;rsquo;t see, or the robot is being teleoperated to get a nice clean take for the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hM1Gd3wbA_U&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter today, helpfully captioned &amp;ldquo;This unassuming robot could sneak into your home.&amp;rdquo;  First of all: i LOVE this SPROINGY LAD, he is doing SO WELL!! him jump!  And he goes up uneven surfaces and stairs &lt;em&gt;super well&lt;/em&gt;.  But let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the actual video footage again, this time through the eyes of a cynical robotics engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We see the lil dude climbing a fence very slowly over the course of a long time-lapse shot (look how fast the trees are shaking).  How long does it take him to fumblingly do this outside the realm of film?  An hour?  How many takes of him falling off the fence before getting to the top are we not seeing?  Also, can he even go over the top of the fence?  I don&amp;rsquo;t think his arrangement of legs will let him push himself onto the other side of the fence, no matter how you control them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The video&amp;rsquo;s main cause for alarm seems to be &amp;ldquo;omg it can go up stairs!!  It can open doors!&amp;rdquo;  Well, okay, it can go up stairs.  So if it gets into your house, it can go up stairs.  And it opens a door by throwing itself at the door, pushing the lever arm &lt;strong&gt;up&lt;/strong&gt; (at which point the door opens a crack), then pushing open the door and going about its business.  My gut instinct is that this demo has probably been hard-coded to successfully open this specific door some of the time.  Certainly I can&amp;rsquo;t see any cameras on the robot to perceive the handle, so the location of the handle relative to the robot seems to be hard-coded &amp;ndash; which makes me think the robot is being teleoperated and the human had to try a bunch of times to get him lined up just right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your door doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a lever-arm-type handle (if it has a round knob, for example), this robot is screwed.  If the handle is lever-arm-type but can&amp;rsquo;t be opened by pulling up, the robot is screwed.  If the door is heavy enough that the (lightweight-looking) robot can&amp;rsquo;t push it open, the robot is screwed.  If the handle is not where the robot expects it to be (e.g. if it is on the right-hand-side of the door), the robot is screwed.  If the door is a sliding door, the robot is screwed.  If there&amp;rsquo;s a screen door that needs to be held out of the way while you open the main door, the robot is screwed.  There&amp;rsquo;s, uh, a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of different kinds of doors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also don&amp;rsquo;t think he&amp;rsquo;s anywhere near ready to pick a lock.  How does he break into a home??  Hope for an open window?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the uninitiated: An encoder is used to measure how much a motor turns (and it&amp;rsquo;s, uh, not a new invention).  Typically on wheeled robots this is used to get odometry data (how far the robot has gone and in which directions), which rapidly builds up error over time, particularly if the wheels slip or lose contact with the ground frequently.  But this is a legged robot that bounces, so I don&amp;rsquo;t see how they can get odometry worth a damn out of the encoders.  That makes me think they&amp;rsquo;re using the encoders as feedback in the control algorithms for the legs here, but truly you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know it from the completely nonsensical captions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notice also that the original audio has been dubbed over.  Now, I don&amp;rsquo;t know for sure how much noise this lad makes, but motors are often pretty loud unless specifically designed to be nice and unobtrusive &amp;ndash; and this looks to me like a research/prototype robot, so I kind of doubt they&amp;rsquo;re spending extra money on the Good Quiet Motors.  Many of the Boston Dynamics robots you see a lot in this context have pneumatic actuation, which requires an air compressor, which can also be very loud (see the original BigDog video).  I am not accepting any assertions that this robot can sneak &lt;strong&gt;anywhere&lt;/strong&gt; until I can hear how much noise he makes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is it gonna do once it gets in my house?? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have arms!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, far from &amp;ldquo;THIS ROBOT CAN BREAK INTO ANY HOME&amp;rdquo;, I have seen 0 evidence so far that he can break into my unlocked garage.  Also, I love him, and he is my very springy son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to get a good idea of the current state of robot manipulation, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JzlsvFN_5HI&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;*.  I want to point out that the QR codes taped to everything are known in the biz as &amp;ldquo;fiducials&amp;rdquo;, and they&amp;rsquo;re letting the robot see where all the stuff is (and how far away it is).  I also want to say that this video is a huge goddamn mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you&amp;rsquo;ll permit me to get serious for a sec, the real risk of advancements in AI technology isn&amp;rsquo;t a movie-type robot rebellion &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s the damage to privacy and justice done by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/28/technology/clearview-ai-privacy-lawsuit.html&#34;&gt;widespread use&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/06/11/clearview-ai-facial-recognition-europe.html&#34;&gt;facial recognition&lt;/a&gt; and the biased (racist, sexist, etc.) and completely non-introspectable classifiers we see in applications like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2017/04/courts-using-ai-sentence-criminals-must-stop-now/&#34;&gt;setting jail time&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G&#34;&gt;hiring and recruiting&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-11-11/apple-card-s-ai-stumble-looks-familiar-to-old-school-banks&#34;&gt;deciding if someone is creditworthy&lt;/a&gt;.  And that&amp;rsquo;s just what&amp;rsquo;s happening today; who knows what new, horrible applications of machine learning will be invented in the coming few years?  But that&amp;rsquo;s kind of a downer to end this post on, so here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g0TaYhjpOfo&#34;&gt;DRC Robot Fall Compilation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* this is kind of a joke, but less than we robotics engineers would like.  For an example of a good robot video about some very recent manipulation research, take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://berkeleyautomation.github.io/dex-net/&#34;&gt;Dex-Net&lt;/a&gt;.  It uses a 5x timelapse, because otherwise the video would be interminably boring to watch, but note how it tells you at what rate the video has been sped up, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t use jump-cuts.  If you see jump-cuts in a robot video, or even just a suspiciously fast cut-away from the robot successfully finishing a task, that&amp;rsquo;s a fairly telltale sign that someone&amp;rsquo;s edited out some hilarious robot fails.  Note also that Dex-Net works in a highly controlled environment and has both a vacuum manipulator and a two-finger gripper to pick up various kinds of objects.  For reasons I won&amp;rsquo;t get into here, it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to compute grasps for vacuum manipulators, but obviously they won&amp;rsquo;t work on all objects &amp;ndash; which is where the 2-finger gripper comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Shiloh&#39;s Guide to Robotics &amp; Software Internships</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/internships/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/internships/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently employed at my *checks notes* seventh internship, which God willing ought to be my last.  Accordingly, I wanted to write up everything I know about internships, before I get employed full-time and forget it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and by the way, if you&amp;rsquo;re in college or fixin&#39; to go to one, you should give &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1238585.html&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; a read.  I had half of a hugely long college advice post in the works, and this said everything I wanted to say way more eloquently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edited 20-Aug-2020 to add the &amp;ldquo;Why internships?&amp;rdquo; section.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-internships&#34;&gt;Why internships?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first version of this post, I made some assumptions, some knowingly and some not: that you, my audience, are an undergraduate student in software/robotics; that you understand vaguely what a software internship is for, career-wise; and that you are already planning to do an internship but don&amp;rsquo;t quite know how to go about snagging one.  My background is such that I had a very deep understanding of the robotics industry and how internships would fit into my career before I even set foot on campus, and it literally did not occur to me that not everyone knows this stuff until my roommate pointed it out to me.  Thus this section of the post, where I assume that you&amp;rsquo;re probably a freshman and try to sell you on the concept that internships are a thing you really, really want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two general career tracks in robotics (and software more broadly) are &amp;ldquo;industry&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;research&amp;rdquo;, and which one of these you go down will determine the best way for you to spend your summers.  Typically, if you&amp;rsquo;re going down the research track, your goal in undergrad is to make yourself as attractive a candidate in grad school admissions as possible (much like how your goal in high school was to make yourself attractive in college admissions).  This usually means research &amp;ndash; what we at MIT call UROPs.  You want to try to get associated with a research lab in undergrad as soon as possible, and spend your summers working on research.  This is all I&amp;rsquo;ll say about the research track; it&amp;rsquo;s not the focus of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the industry track, you instead want to spend your summers doing internships.  Jobs you apply for after graduating college will expect you to have done at least one software internship, and probably several.  You can (and should) start getting internships as early as the summer after your freshman year.  At MIT, I also knew people who did externships (mini-internships), particularly during IAP (MIT starts the spring semester in February; you can spend the month of January, known as IAP, doing externships, taking mini-classes, or just recovering from burnout), and if you&amp;rsquo;re taking a gap year or a leave of absence, you might want to spend part of it doing an internship.  If you&amp;rsquo;ve had little luck so far with getting summer internships or spent a while on the research track and decided it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for you, doing a bunch of these smaller off-cycle internships/externships can be a great way to get more experience on your resume, and the application process for them tends to be much less competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A software or robotics engineering internship should be paid.  Generally, the company will find a project for you that is scoped to take an undergrad roughly three months to finish and (hopefully) interesting, but not really business-critical.  They&amp;rsquo;ll also assign you a mentor/supervisor.  At some companies, you may have a separate supervisor (your boss) and mentor (advises you on professional development); at others these may be the same person, or the mentor role won&amp;rsquo;t really exist.  You&amp;rsquo;ll probably have the best experience if there is some kind of explicit mentorship happening and both your mentor and your supervisor are excited about having an intern.  The overall goal is for you to get some work experience in your field of interest and maybe also some professional mentorship.  (The benefit to the company is not really useful labor from its interns; instead, what it wants is to recruit the best interns as full-time employees in the future.  Its hope is that you&amp;rsquo;ll be more likely to choose the company you had a great internship at over other companies that you&amp;rsquo;ve only interacted with in interviews.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reiterate: it&amp;rsquo;s never too early to get an internship.  Large tech companies often have intern programs specifically for freshmen (and large companies with established processes will also help you learn software best-practices).  Smaller companies and startups don&amp;rsquo;t typically have elaborately organized internship programs, but can also be less selective.  MIT has a special freshmen-only section of career fair; make sure to check if your college does that, because talking to five companies in a row that by policy can only hire juniors will make you feel lower than dirt.  Very early in your college career you may not have any actual coursework to speak of (and this is not helped by the stupid internship recruiting cycle that starts in SEPTEMBER), but hopefully you have a couple high school or personal projects that prove you know, at least a little bit, what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.  There will also be companies that have sensible expectations of freshmen, and it is definitely possible to get internships at them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, rant over, back to the rest of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;networking&#34;&gt;Networking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hey, why is networking first?&lt;/em&gt;  Networking is important.  Networking is hands down &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; best way to find internships (and, uh, jobs), because you can completely avoid the traditional interview gauntlet in which you beg a company to please bestow upon you an internship crumb.  Instead, you float the knowledge to your network that you are Looking For An Internship, and you get responses like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should intern for my cool startup!  Send me an email later and we can work out the offer details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I know this company is hiring interns, let me introduce you to the intern program coordinator&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should intern for my company!  Send me an email when you apply and I&amp;rsquo;ll talk to the recruiter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, a friend of mine (who had, at the time, just graduated from high school) wanted to intern at a particular robotics team.  The manager of this team knew him through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hbrobotics.org&#34;&gt;Homebrew Robotics Club&lt;/a&gt;, and very much wanted to hire him as an intern.  However, as a matter of policy this team could not hire any intern who was not a PhD student or postdoc.  To do an end-run around the policy, my friend was hired as an intern at a contracting company that he was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; connected with through the HBRC, then contracted to work for the robotics team.  At no point did any interviews take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important here to understand: by networking, I do not mean the thing where you email (or Linkedin-message) random people and go to events where you trade crappy business cards with other people who are There To Network.  You want to make &lt;em&gt;genuine friends&lt;/em&gt; with people who are in the industry you want to be in, but a few years older.  I think the best way to do this is to attend some casual event that lots of people in your industry go to, and make friends there in the normal way.  You also want to start as early as possible; the process kind of snowballs once you know enough people.  Here&amp;rsquo;s how I built my network:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending the aforementioned Homebrew Robotics Club.  I started doing this when I was 7, but the club has attendees of all ages, including a good few robotics industry professionals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through the HBRC, I met the two founders of Fetch Robotics, who invited me to intern there.  This was (a) a cool internship and (b) got me onto the Willow Garage board game night mailing list.  Willow Garage no longer exists, but its diaspora still get together ~every week for board games and chat about robotics inside baseball.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attending board game night.  This helped me get to know a bunch of other people in the Willow Garage diaspora network who don&amp;rsquo;t go to the HBRC.  Eventually, I was offered my Iron Ox internship at a board game night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separately from this, one day I was messaged on Linkedin by a recruiter for a Playground Global portfolio company.  Playground is an incubator with a good few robotics startups; it also has weekly happy hours, which let me meet other people at Playground portfolio companies.  I met my mentor at my current internship, also a Playground company, last summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously not all of this is actionable (particularly if you do not live in the SF Bay Area), but this is what I did/knew how to do.  You&amp;rsquo;ll have to do your own legwork, if you live elsewhere, on what events (if any) are in your area.  (Also, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in robotics and can swing an internship in the Bay Area for the summer, I strongly recommend attending the HBRC.  If nothing else, it&amp;rsquo;s fun!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear that you can also get good results, if you are an undergrad at a research college, by doing research in a lab and insinuating yourself into their lab meetings and other informal events.  I&amp;rsquo;ve always been abjectly crap at this one, but if you can get yourself to be less shy than me it&amp;rsquo;d probably work well.  Also on the academia side of networking, conferences sound cool, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to one.  (one day I dream of finally going to ROSCon&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Career fairs are IME mostly useless, and I say this as an MIT student.  Allegedly companies are clamoring to hire us, and my career fair experience is still &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;re not hiring sophomores&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;re only hiring grad students&amp;rdquo; (so why are you at the undergrad career fair?) or &amp;ldquo;hm, we&amp;rsquo;re really looking for someone who has 10 years of C++ experience and will accept $15/hour&amp;rdquo; (SO WHY ARE YOU AT THE UNDERGRAD CAREER FAIR).  Also, the vast majority of the companies there are just generic software places, and I&amp;rsquo;m looking for robotics jobs specifically; maybe a pure-software person would have better luck.  But career fairs still put you through the standard recruitment process, and the goal of networking is to bypass that process to the greatest possible extent because you know the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, I would still go to career fairs though.  Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll get lucky.  And a free T-shirt = one more day to procrastinate on laundry, which is nothing to sneeze at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to figure out what your college&amp;rsquo;s career-relevant mailing lists and so forth are, and get on them.  At MIT, Course 6 (EECS) has a mailing list called eecs-jobs-announce for job announcements, and a Piazza forum called 6.AcAd where people often compare intern pay rates; robotics-specific jobs are often posted to the robotics-related mailing list.  I&amp;rsquo;ve also seen job announcements on class mailing lists for robotics classes like 6.141.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and keep your Linkedin profile up-to-date.  Most of the Linkedin messages I get are from people who clearly haven&amp;rsquo;t read my profile (I got one as a sophomore asking if I wanted to be a Senior Robotics Engineer &amp;ndash; like, buddy, I&amp;rsquo;m not even a senior in college), but sometimes cool stuff comes in over Linkedin if you have a bunch of the good keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application timeline for summer software internships starts in the fall, which is silly.  Typically, only bigger and better-established companies will have their shit together this far in advance, so many startups will still be available to you if you start looking in Jan/Feb.  But the big career fair is probably in the fall, the application deadline for my Google Engineering Practicum internship was, IIRC, October 31, and (particularly in the excitement of your freshman year) it&amp;rsquo;s easy to let these deadlines slip by.  It helps to be organized about it &amp;ndash; make a list of companies you&amp;rsquo;re interested in and add all their relevant application tasks and deadlines to your calendar/planner/task tracking system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also in the fall, if you have a solid network, I would recommend emailing people in your network and asking about potential internship opportunities.  Since most of my network is startup-focused, often the companies I email haven&amp;rsquo;t yet started recruiting interns, but it never hurts to be early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, the internship application process consists of a coding challenge or coding assessment over the phone, then maybe one or two technical interviews, then an offer call.  Google also for some reason wanted an application essay.  There typically aren&amp;rsquo;t onsites; I had two onsite interviews at Boston area startups and one at a company in Palo Alto, which I did over my winter break because I was conveniently at home in Sunnyvale.  (I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have invited me for the onsite if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been from the area.  Nobody flies intern candidates anywhere, is my point.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you anticipate a lot of coding challenges it&amp;rsquo;s probably worthwhile to practice a bit on Leetcode or similar.  Also make sure to review the most common languages you think you&amp;rsquo;ll see; I have, in the past, completely bombed a coding challenge because it was in C++ and I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough C++ experience at the time to write anything remotely sensible on the clock.  (It still takes me 3x as long to do anything in C++, compared to Python.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come January, many big companies&#39; intern recruiting cycles will be over, but others may not have gotten the memo yet, and lots of startups will still probably be looking.  MIT has a second, smaller career fair at the end of January called XFair, and a third career fair a little later in the spring semester.  I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to the spring career fair because we&amp;rsquo;re not given the day off and I inevitably have a fully-booked schedule of classes for whatever random Tuesday it happens to be, but XFair tends to be smaller, calmer, and more startup-biased, and I honestly think it&amp;rsquo;s been at least as valuable for me as the fall career fair.  If anyone you emailed earlier in the fall hasn&amp;rsquo;t responded yet, this is also a great time to poke them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not personally tried this, but if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in a startup where you don&amp;rsquo;t know anyone and they haven&amp;rsquo;t yet set up an official intern program, you could definitely just email them anyway (&amp;ldquo;Hello [cofounder/CTO], I&amp;rsquo;m a robotics/CS/underwater basketweaving student at XYZ University, and I&amp;rsquo;m interested in interning at your company because blah blah blah&amp;hellip;&amp;quot;) and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By March/April, most internship recruiting will be over.  You could try using your network to do a Hail Mary pass, but at this point if you haven&amp;rsquo;t found an internship you probably want to start looking for a summer research position or something (this is not a diss of research; grad students looking to hire undergrads for their projects just don&amp;rsquo;t tend to do things all that far in advance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this whole process, you will have to send a lot of professional-sounding emails.  The main way I figured out how to do the professional-sounding email tone is by binge-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.askamanager.org/&#34;&gt;Ask a Manager&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-do-career-fair&#34;&gt;How to do career fair&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My procedure for every career fair is pretty similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days before the fair, I go through the list of companies that will be there, and make a list of all the robotics companies.  There are usually 6-8 of these (out of the hundreds of companies at the fair).  I further narrow these down by crossing off all the companies that seem very boring or that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to work for.  Then I copy this list onto a notecard, which I stick in my nondescriptly professional fake-leather folder, along with ~20 copies of my resume.  I always get really paranoid and print out way too many copies of my resume (what if there&amp;rsquo;s an emergency that can only be solved by a small integer number of paper airplanes???) and I never use more than like 5.  This is the secret second reason why &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bitchesgetriches.com/how-to-write-a-resume-so-you-actually-have-a-prayer-of-getting-hired/&#34;&gt;your resume should fit in one page&lt;/a&gt;: if it&amp;rsquo;s double-sided, you can&amp;rsquo;t use the backs of your unused resumes as scratch paper later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to not bring too much stuff with me to the fair, because I know I&amp;rsquo;ll be collecting half a dozen tote bags full of miscellaneous career fair crap later.  I keep a pad of paper and a pen in my folio and my keys + Leatherman tool in my pocket.  I also bring a pair of concert earplugs (specifically Etymotics), which don&amp;rsquo;t help as much as I wish they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I check in to the fair, I usually get handed some kind of map that shows me where all the booths are.  I take a few minutes to mark on the map all the companies on my list, and plan a route that means I have to spend the absolute minimum possible time in the hellishly noisy halls.  Then I start talking to my companies of interest.  At this stage of the procedure I don&amp;rsquo;t collect any swag, because it&amp;rsquo;s really awkward to juggle five water bottles as you try to give someone your resume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to remember to ask a few questions at all of my companies of interest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the intern program like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[if talking to an engineer] So what do you personally do, on a day-to-day basis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your tech stack?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(this is the really important one) &lt;strong&gt;What are my next steps here?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always try to ask the &amp;ldquo;next steps&amp;rdquo; question last, so I actually have a hope of remembering all the details, and then I leave and try to find a quiet spot to scribble down what I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to do.  I am never fully consistent about this, but a scribbled note that says the company name and &amp;ldquo;wait for email&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;fill out form on flyer&amp;rdquo; is infinitely better than nothing.  The other questions are partly so I can get a general impression about the company but mostly so the people at the booth think I&amp;rsquo;m a Smart Person who Asks Good Questions and not some dweeb who just walks up and silently hands them a resume.  Also, if they ask &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; a question I have to get them to repeat it like three times because I can&amp;rsquo;t hear, and I am not very coherent when put on the spot; I feel like the interaction leaves them with a much better impression if I also ask some questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I&amp;rsquo;m done talking to all my companies of interest, I spend the rest of my time at career fair collecting as much swag as possible before my legs give out, then stumble back to my dorm and crash on the bed, where I immediately muck up my career fair makeup and ponytail and get lint all over my black pants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the career fair I try to interpret my mysterious notes about my next steps and follow them to the best of my ability.  If there were no mysterious notes, or if I can&amp;rsquo;t read the mysterious notes, or if the mysterious notes seem to imply that the next step is on their end, just to be safe and make sure they didn&amp;rsquo;t forget about me I send an email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi [person&amp;rsquo;s name, if I was handed a specific person&amp;rsquo;s business card],&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet you at the MIT Career Fair yesterday!  Thanks for taking the time to speak with me about [year] internships.  My resume is attached for your reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks,
[my name]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;rsquo;s important to remember to actually attach the resume here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the few weeks post-career-fair, I tend to receive a lot of emails about coding challenges and interview dates and such things, and I suck at keeping track of these.  If you receive an email with an action item for you, make sure to immediately log it in your to-do list or task tracker.  However, and this has historically been one of my weak points, if you receive an email and the next action item is on the company&amp;rsquo;s end, you should add to your to-do list something to the effect of &amp;ldquo;If [thing] not yet received, follow up with [company]&amp;rdquo;, and set this task to be due in a few days or whenever the company told you you&amp;rsquo;d receive [thing].  This prevents the scenario where the company says they&amp;rsquo;ll send you a coding challenge, forgets to send the coding challenge, bugs you in a week like &amp;ldquo;hey we noticed you failed to complete the coding challenge by our deadline,&amp;rdquo; and then gets shirty with you when you admit you did not receive the coding challenge and forgot to follow up with them about it.  Companies are often kind of disorganized about career-fair follow-up, so this sort of thing happens more frequently than you&amp;rsquo;d think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above all, don&amp;rsquo;t feel discouraged if the outcome of all your career fair efforts amounts to a wet fart.  It happens, often to very smart and qualified people, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a referendum on your actual value.  Also, applying to internships is a numbers game, and the numbers are very much not in your favor if you&amp;rsquo;re doing anything other than Generic Software or if you&amp;rsquo;re a freshman/sophomore (many companies have blanket policies preventing them from hiring underclassmen).  I think it&amp;rsquo;s still worth going to career fair if you&amp;rsquo;re in one of these numbers-disadvantaged categories, because the practice is valuable and will help you freak out less when you become a senior and Uber or whoever will finally deign to talk to you.  Just, you know, keep your expectations low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to discuss interview prep here; I think it&amp;rsquo;s been adequately covered elsewhere on the Internet.  Briefly: Read &lt;em&gt;Cracking the Coding Interview&lt;/em&gt;, maybe do some practice problems on Leetcode, and have material from your data structures/algorithms class(es) fresh in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wage-negotiation&#34;&gt;Wage negotiation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wage negotiation scares me a lot, since I am anxious and hate confrontation.  However, I do like having money, which is a pretty decent incentive to put some effort into getting over this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of advice out there on salary negotiation &amp;ndash; my favorites being &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/01/23/salary-negotiation/&#34;&gt;patio11&amp;rsquo;s classic post&lt;/a&gt; and this two-part series (&lt;a href=&#34;https://haseebq.com/my-ten-rules-for-negotiating-a-job-offer/&#34;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://haseebq.com/how-not-to-bomb-your-offer-negotiation/&#34;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;).  This advice is largely geared towards people who are interviewing for full-time roles; intern pay works a little differently.  As an intern, you generally get paid less, and you&amp;rsquo;re being hired for a temporary period, e.g. a summer.  Typically, interns are also paid by the hour.  Also, companies (unless they are very small and new) usually have a standard intern rate.  Some startups may be amenable to changing this if you negotiate, whereas a big company like Google is take-it-or-leave-it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a software engineer or software adjacent internship, your rate will basically be a linear function of the number of years you&amp;rsquo;ve been in college.  It&amp;rsquo;s a super good idea to get an idea of what rate you want/feel you deserve by talking to other students at your school; at MIT, the 6.AcAd Piazza forum was the place to discuss internship wages.  Wages will also depend to some extent on cost-of-living in your location, so keep an eye out for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the interests of transparency, my past internships, all of which have been in Silicon Valley/SF Bay:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High school: free lunch, small robotics consulting company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gap year before college: $25/hour, robotics startup (~30 employees and hiring rapidly, maybe 5 other interns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-freshman year: $27.50/hour, Google (Engineering Practicum).  I also got a $9k &amp;ldquo;relocation bonus&amp;rdquo;, even though I&amp;rsquo;m literally from Sunnyvale and spent the summer living with my parents, and I told the recruiter this.  After the internship they gave me a return offer for $32/hour, which I turned down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-sophomore year: $35/hour and $1000/month relocation, robotics startup (~10 employees, 1 other intern).  Again, I don&amp;rsquo;t know why they gave me a relocation bonus, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining.  (Actually, I just looked at the email thread, and apparently I told them the full specifics of the Google return offer with &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; relocation bonus.  Uhh&amp;hellip; negotiation, baby?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-junior year: $35/hour, robotics startup (~5 employees, 0 other interns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently (post-senior year): $55/hour, robotics startup (~20 employees, 2 other interns)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(for context, I&amp;rsquo;m doing a 5th-year MEng program at MIT, which is why I have a post-senior year internship)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for software internships and a startup gives you the &amp;ldquo;oooh nooo we can&amp;rsquo;t possibly pay you more than [crap amount] we&amp;rsquo;re just a little bitty startup waaaaah you can&amp;rsquo;t expect us to pay google wages&amp;rdquo; sob story, they&amp;rsquo;re ripping you off.  If a startup is so poorly funded or mismanaged that they can&amp;rsquo;t pay an intern competitively, that can also be a red flag.  Now, if you&amp;rsquo;re willing to put up with it financially and you think the internship has something else to offer, you might decide to go for it anyway.  But that&amp;rsquo;s, you know, a decision you can make from an informed position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a startup is on a rapid hiring spree, that tends to mean the company is well-funded and in a good position (although I&amp;rsquo;ve also seen VCs encourage startups to hire way outside their means in an attempt to drive the company to either succeed or fail fast).  Startups in general can be more volatile, even on the timescale of an internship, because the startup industry moves fast.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t at all likely to happen to you, but in the worst-case a startup could hire you as a summer intern in January and be out-of-business by June.  As with investing, it all depends on your risk tolerance.  It&amp;rsquo;s super valid to ask about a company&amp;rsquo;s stability and funding situation in the interview (and you&amp;rsquo;ll want to mentally translate this from &amp;ldquo;rose-tinted stories told to VCs&amp;rdquo; to normal human language).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the company asks what I would expect to be paid (during the offer call or late in the hiring pipeline), I typically just give them a range off the bat, where the low number is an hourly rate I feel is &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; for MIT course 6 students in my class year and the high number is maybe $10-15 more.  Intern hiring is less tolerant of a bunch of negotiation henning-around, and I feel pretty well informed about reasonable intern pay.  If they ask me what I expect to be paid in one of the earlier phone interviews I&amp;rsquo;m more evasive: &amp;ldquo;well, I was paid X amount last summer, so I would expect an increase that reflects what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned since then&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, one more thing &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s also super valid to ask about the company&amp;rsquo;s overtime policies.  At my past internships the rule has been time-and-a-half for working over 8 hours a day, but some companies are chill with you staying a couple extra hours because you were in the zone and lost track of time or you wanted to eat the free dinner at the company cafeteria, and some are more strict about not wanting you to work any overtime.  If this matters to you, an email thread after the offer call is the perfect time to discuss it.  The full, legal agreement will be laid out in the offer letter, but you won&amp;rsquo;t usually be sent this until you and the company have agreed on the details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;okay-so-i-have-one-or-more-companies-offering-to-hire-me-now-what-do-i-do&#34;&gt;Okay, so I have one or more companies offering to hire me, now what do I do??&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have no other companies still in-pipeline, then your decision is pretty straightforward.  Unfortunately, real life doesn&amp;rsquo;t tend to work out this neatly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten an offer you like well enough to take it without waiting for the rest of the companies in pipeline to come to a decision, go for it!  The company will probably make you the offer over the phone, so make sure you ask to get the details in writing, and have a pad of paper handy to scribble down the relevant numbers as you hear them.  I would recommend not accepting the offer in this initial phone call; take a few days to think about it, then email the recruiter back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you&amp;rsquo;d like to stall the offering company and light a fire under the still-in-pipeline companies to get you an offer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[To the offering company]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you so much for the offer!  I&amp;rsquo;m currently in the interview process with another company, so I&amp;rsquo;ll need a little more time to consider it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Your decision whether you want to namedrop the other company; I personally wouldn&amp;rsquo;t.)  If the offer has an explicit deadline that you want to extend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it possible for you to give me until [date] to make my decision?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your school may also set an earliest possible offer deadline or prohibit companies from making offers that expire too quickly &amp;ndash; at MIT these &lt;a href=&#34;https://capd.mit.edu/employers/recruiting-policies-and-resources&#34;&gt;recruiting policies&lt;/a&gt; are set by CAPD and companies that violate them may be banned from the career fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[To the still-in-pipeline company]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to let you know that I&amp;rsquo;ve received another internship offer which I need to respond to by [date].  As I&amp;rsquo;m still very much interested in [your company], will it be possible for you to complete the interview process by this time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would give them a date a little ways in advance of the true deadline.  If the other company is very famous you might consider name-dropping them here, but I&amp;rsquo;ve had this blow up on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do you actually decide which offer to take?  I generally decide based on some combination of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how interesting/fun I think the company will be to work for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how valuable I think it&amp;rsquo;ll be from a networking perspective&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;whether it will teach me new skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how different it is from things I&amp;rsquo;ve already done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically I also lean towards startups, because I think they&amp;rsquo;re more fun to work at than big companies.  However, I assume you the reader are not a clone of me, so it&amp;rsquo;s probably worth interning at both startups and established companies and seeing which one you like better.  I would also note that at Google specifically, if you apply as a standard intern, you have to accept your offer &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; you get matched with a team, and you&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to be matched with a team that has any relevance to, say, robotics.  Which is fine if you&amp;rsquo;re open to a bunch of different topics; less great if you want to specialize.  I don&amp;rsquo;t know how many other large companies do this, but be on the lookout for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you take your offer, you&amp;rsquo;ll be sent an offer letter, an NDA (non-disclosure agreement), and possibly an invention assignment agreement.  Non-competes are illegal in the state of California and kind of ridiculous to give an intern anyway, so I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect you to see one.  The invention assignment agreement assigns any IP you create during your internship to the company &amp;ndash; &lt;strong&gt;read this carefully&lt;/strong&gt; to make sure it doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to stuff you do in your spare time on your own equipment or stuff you&amp;rsquo;ve done before the internship started, and cause a ruckus if it seems overly broad!  There may be a place where you write down all the IP you want to explicitly exclude from the agreement (e.g. a patent, if you have one).  Everything else you should read carefully, and if you see anything you&amp;rsquo;re uncomfortable with you can definitely ask your recruiter or point of contact with the company about it.  Finally, this is &lt;strong&gt;not legal advice&lt;/strong&gt; and I am &lt;strong&gt;not a lawyer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often I find I&amp;rsquo;ve accepted an internship offer in the fall and then a while later another interesting company messages me on Linkedin or I talk to them at XFair or something.  This isn&amp;rsquo;t a bad thing!  You have many opportunities to do internships!  If it&amp;rsquo;s an email or similar, I might say&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reaching out!  Unfortunately I&amp;rsquo;ve already accepted an offer for Summer [year], but I&amp;rsquo;m definitely interested in discussing future internships with [company].  Let&amp;rsquo;s stay in touch!  I&amp;rsquo;ve attached my current resume, and I&amp;rsquo;ll check back in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a spring career fair, you can do the usual career fair chat about the company&amp;rsquo;s technology and your skills/past experience.  Make sure to mention that you&amp;rsquo;ve accepted an offer already (so you&amp;rsquo;re not &amp;ldquo;leading them on&amp;rdquo;), &amp;ldquo;but it&amp;rsquo;s never too early to start looking for [year+1] internships, right?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you do then have to put in your calendar or to-do list a reminder to actually follow up with the company in the fall.  (It&amp;rsquo;s always best to be proactive; don&amp;rsquo;t trust that the company is organized; things can always fall through the cracks).  You may also want to contact in the fall any companies that you were interviewing with, liked, but ultimately turned down.  It&amp;rsquo;s best to do all of this fairly early in the fall, particularly if your current internship might make a return offer, but in any case it&amp;rsquo;s great if your resume is the first in the pile come fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This follow-up fall email is a great place to write a couple casual paragraphs about what you&amp;rsquo;ve been up to since they last heard from you (e.g. anything you learned in your summer internship), but whether or not you do this, you should re-attach an updated version of your resume.  This may seem super redundant, but companies often have processes such that they only &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo; the information you have given them in your resume (presumably because this makes their &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1177349.html&#34;&gt;coordinative communication&lt;/a&gt; smoother and more standardized).  The wildest version of this is that last fall I had a company email me asking me to &lt;em&gt;edit my resume&lt;/em&gt; so it had information about my MEng program, because apparently this was the only way they could put me in the summer-internship stack and not the new-grad hiring stack.  Now, this is a kind of crap experience for the candidate, but once you know about it you can start playing their game (in this case, attach your resume every time you email the company since you last edited it, and also anytime you want to give them a backup copy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thats-it&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck and godspeed!  If any of this advice works out for you, or if there&amp;rsquo;s anything else you&amp;rsquo;d add, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about it &amp;ndash; email me at &lt;code&gt;shilohc (at) mit (dot) edu&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Criticizing design articles because I can</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/design_criticism_01/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/design_criticism_01/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://uxdesign.cc/design-better-forms-96fadca0f49c&#34;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; on form design seems perfectly innocuous.  It&amp;rsquo;s a helpful guide that lays out best practices and briefly describes why they&amp;rsquo;re better than the obvious alternative.  But then I got to this part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-ask&#34;&gt;Why ask?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omit optional fields and think of other ways to collect data.  Always ask yourself if the question can be inferred, postponed, or completely excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, we&amp;rsquo;re doing great so far.  The more unnecessary data you ask for, the more likely you are to violate your users&#39; privacy, and incidentally the more likely you are to exclude &amp;ldquo;edge-case&amp;rdquo; users.  For example, Basler makes you fill out a brief biographical form in order to &lt;em&gt;download software for their cameras&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; name, address, and salutation (select exactly one of Mr. or Ms.) are all required fields.  No joy for nonbinary people or people with doctorates.  As a nonbinary person I am never going to let this one go, because I was essentially forced to misgender myself to do my job correctly when I worked at an otherwise fantastic internship that used Basler cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data entry is increasingly automated.  For example, mobile and wearable devices collect large amounts of data without the user&amp;rsquo;s conscious awareness.  Think of ways you can leverage social, conversational UI, SMS, email, voice, OCR, location, fingerprint, biometric, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I DON&amp;rsquo;T LIKE THE SOUND OF THAT AT ALL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So&amp;hellip; what you&amp;rsquo;re saying, essentially, is that instead of actually asking users for data you don&amp;rsquo;t strictly need (so that they could leave it off the form if they don&amp;rsquo;t want you to have it), you want designers to collect it by other means, &amp;ldquo;without the user&amp;rsquo;s conscious awareness&amp;rdquo; if necessary??  Let me be clear: this is unethical.  Bad designer!  No cookie!  Consent is important for all things in life, including sex and collection of user data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fastcompany.com/3053406/how-apple-is-giving-design-a-bad-name&#34;&gt;How Apple Is Giving Design A Bad Name&lt;/a&gt; was written by Don Norman and Bruce Tognazzini.  I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything bad to say about the actual design recommendations in this article, but I do have a beef with its casual ableism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what it says in the context of a discussion about how the Apple system font, which uses thin lines and low contrast, is hard to read, taking as an example a middle-aged woman who used the iOS accessibility settings to embiggen the system font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to note that she did not have defective vision. She just didn’t have the eyesight of a 17-year-old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What kind of design philosophy requires millions of its users to have to pretend they are disabled in order to be able to use the product?  Apple could have designed its phone so that the majority of people could read and use the phone without having to label themselves as needy, disabled, and requiring assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I don&amp;rsquo;t particularly care for the implication that being disabled is somehow bad or shameful.  The (not-particularly-well-)hidden message here is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it&amp;rsquo;s insulting to the user to force them to identify themselves as disabled, or use accessibility tools meant for disabled people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user here didn&amp;rsquo;t have &lt;em&gt;defective vision&lt;/em&gt;, oh no!  She wasn&amp;rsquo;t really &lt;em&gt;disabled&lt;/em&gt;.  Because being disabled is &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.  Now, the problem here seems to be that Apple has designed for the ability of exactly one type of user (our hypothetical 17-year-old), and therefore excludes&amp;hellip; other users&amp;hellip; because they don&amp;rsquo;t have the same level of ability&amp;hellip; But this isn&amp;rsquo;t a disability issue!  Because being disabled is &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.  The article goes on to say that this woman then enabled the accessibility tool for enlarging text, which makes some text run off the screen in other apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to me, both of these things are failures of accessibility!  Both the insufficient contrast in the system font, and the fact that the accessibility tool makes some text unreadable, are accessibility problems.  Design for accessibility helps everyone, even people who don&amp;rsquo;t think of themselves as disabled.  And stigmatizing disability and the use of accessibility tools is harmful*; there&amp;rsquo;s no good reason for this, and it may deter someone from using tools that can help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m not done.  Let&amp;rsquo;s look at this quote again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple could have designed its phone so that the majority of people could read and use the phone without having to label themselves as needy, disabled, and requiring assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using accessibility tools, says the article, means you are labeling yourself as &amp;ldquo;needy&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;disabled&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;requiring assistance&amp;rdquo;, which it conflates by listing them like this.  The concept that any disabled person must be in need of assistance from any abled person in the vicinity is &amp;ndash; well, first of all, it&amp;rsquo;s false, but it&amp;rsquo;s also actively dangerous to disabled people.  For example, many wheelchair users report that abled people tend to try to &amp;ldquo;help&amp;rdquo; them by suddenly pushing their chairs, which can, and regularly does, injure the wheelchair user.  In addition, if the disabled person refuses &amp;ldquo;help&amp;rdquo;, the abled person often gets angry about it.  Please understand: a disabled person is not &amp;ldquo;needy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;requiring assistance&amp;rdquo; just because they are existing, somewhere.  Do not, do not, do not assume that a disabled person requires assistance unless they are actually asking you for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, someone who enables accessibility options on their phone is not &amp;ldquo;needy&amp;rdquo;; they have used the tools at their disposal to help themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning more about accessibility and disability, the disability rights and neurodiversity movements are great places to start.  I&amp;rsquo;d also recommend reading about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_model_of_disability&#34;&gt;social model of disability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* We can also see a pretty clear pattern where people undergoing the normal course of aging &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; thinking of themselves as &amp;ldquo;disabled&amp;rdquo;, due to this stigma.  Because of this, they injure themselves by refusing to use mobility aids, or suffer through refusing other accessibility tools because they&amp;rsquo;re not going to &amp;ldquo;give in&amp;rdquo;.  Many older adults also judge younger invisibly disabled people, because a 20-year-old couldn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;possibly&lt;/em&gt; need a cane for any legitimate reason, and this can result in verbal or even physical abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would make this post rhetorically prettier to have a third example here, but unfortunately I don&amp;rsquo;t have one at the moment.  That&amp;rsquo;s all for today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further reading: &lt;a href=&#34;https://m.signalvnoise.com/move-slowly-and-fix-things/&#34;&gt;Move Slowly and Fix Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>That Fitbit rant</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/fitbit/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/fitbit/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While we&amp;rsquo;re at it, here&amp;rsquo;s another design rant that&amp;rsquo;s been percolating within me like a fine wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I have a Fitbit.  Due to my chronic illness I need to keep an eye on my (unusually high) heart rate, which is why I originally bought the thing; it turns out to also be very useful for tracking my sleep.  I do not give a shit about weight loss and I actively do not want my Fitbit to tell me about it; in the past I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with tracking calories and I very nearly gave myself an eating disorder, so I do not want my exercise tracker to talk to me about weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fitbit and its app, at seemingly every opportunity, want to talk to me about weight.  I&amp;rsquo;ve configured the homescreen of my app to remove &amp;ldquo;calories burned&amp;rdquo;, food logging, and weight tracking, which is all the customization I have in my control.  However, for my current device (the Inspire HR), I can&amp;rsquo;t select a watch face that will show me my heart rate and the date without also showing me &amp;ldquo;calories burned&amp;rdquo;, and my device doesn&amp;rsquo;t support custom watch faces.  When my heart rate goes above 100 BPM (which frequently happens while I am sitting down doing nothing), the app helpfully informs me that I am in the &amp;ldquo;fat burn zone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last iOS app redesign now shows me &amp;ldquo;tips&amp;rdquo; when I launch the app, which I can&amp;rsquo;t disable, only close as they appear.  Lots of them are about weight tracking, calories, food, and weight loss, and even in the ones that aren&amp;rsquo;t, diet talk sneaks in.  Today I was informed that &amp;ldquo;Keeping a healthy sleep routine is like maintaining a good diet &amp;ndash; every day counts.&amp;rdquo;  Once I tried their &amp;ldquo;Intro to Healthy Habits&amp;rdquo; guided program, in the hopes that it would remind me to do an exercise occasionally, and it mostly boiled down to sending me push notifications about food tracking and weight.  When you get started with this program, you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to pick a goal weight.  This is, apparently, the only possible &amp;ldquo;healthy habits&amp;rdquo; goal Fitbit thinks you can have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not the only person with a Fitbit who uses it for something that the designers didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to expect.  For example, I know of a disabled person with mobility issues who uses the step counting/step goal feature to warn her when she&amp;rsquo;s taken too many steps, because she can cause herself permanent injury by going too far over the limit.  But the weight thing seems pretty egregious: lots of people struggle with disordered eating, which can take many forms, including compulsive exercise and calorie tracking.  I am not arguing that Fitbit should remove these tracking capabilities entirely; however, Fitbit is actively alienating people who have struggled with disordered eating by not allowing its users to disable all mentions of weight and calories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s not even getting into the weight-science aspect.  I&amp;rsquo;m definitely not an expert here, and diet/nutrition science kind of seems like a mess, but there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17469900/&#34;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; that losing weight and keeping it off long-term isn&amp;rsquo;t possible through diet alone, and there&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25614201/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fat overshoot&amp;rdquo; effect&lt;/a&gt; that can cause you to gain more weight than you originally lost (possibly due to the starvation response).  As with everything biological, weight and body composition is regulated by &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20200106162146/https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/04/26/anorexia-and-metabolic-set-point/&#34;&gt;a nasty, complex control system&lt;/a&gt; whose precise behavior is dependent on your genetics, and which is interconnected with all the other complex biological systems in weird ways, and which isn&amp;rsquo;t very well-understood, but which we insist on trying to mess with anyway.  So, personally, I think that the responsible thing for Fitbit to do would be to make sure its users are at least a little bit aware that there&amp;rsquo;s more complexity here than a straightforward calories in -&amp;gt; calories out model, and stop implying that permanent weight loss is not only possible-and-desirable-for-everyone but also so easy that their little wristwatch can help you pull it off.  (And IMO trying to lose weight is probably not a good idea unless you really know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing and have done a lot more research on weight science than me.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; solution to the &amp;ldquo;pushiness&amp;rdquo; of the Fitbit WRT weight loss has been to use the Fitbit app as little as possible and slurp out my data using the Fitbit API.  Which is obviously not a solution that&amp;rsquo;s accessible to your average non-technical user.  And even for a technical user like me, trying to implement OAuth2 to Fitbit&amp;rsquo;s satisfaction is pretty annoying (especially since the docs &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.fitbit.com/build/reference/web-api/basics/#app-types&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.fitbit.com/build/reference/web-api/oauth2/#implicit-grant-flow&#34;&gt;inconsistent&lt;/a&gt; about what flavors of token you can use with the &amp;ldquo;Personal&amp;rdquo; app type).  But damn it, I&amp;rsquo;m going to build my own Fitbit data viewer &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; so I can avoid having any contact whatsoever with the app that Fitbit has designed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Design: Edge Cases and Legibility</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/design_legibility/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/design_legibility/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://muledesign.com/2017/07/a-designers-code-of-ethics&#34;&gt;A Designer&amp;rsquo;s Code of Ethics&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-designer-does-not-believe-in-edge-cases&#34;&gt;A designer does not believe in edge cases.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you decide who you’re designing for, you’re making an implicit statement about who you’re not designing for. For years we referred to people who weren’t crucial to our products’ success as “edge cases”. We were marginalizing people. And we were making a decision that there were people in the world whose problems weren’t worth solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook now claims to have two billion users. 1% of two billion people, which most products would consider an edge case, is twenty million people. Those are the people at the margins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When you call something an edge case, you’re really just defining the limits of what you care about.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Eric Meyer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the trans people who get caught on the edges of “real names” projects. These are the single moms who get caught on the edges of “both parents must sign” permission slips. These are the elderly immigrants who show up to vote and can’t get ballots in their native tongues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are not edge cases. They are human beings, and we owe them our best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think the main issue is that designers think consciously about an edge case and decide not to care about it.  That is an issue &amp;ndash; but to me, the bigger problem is that there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of edge cases that just&amp;hellip; don&amp;rsquo;t occur to the designer, or anyone else involved in the product.  Designers wind up making a lot of assumptions subconsciously, without even realizing what&amp;rsquo;s happening.  Thus, it&amp;rsquo;s not enough to just say &amp;ldquo;oh, I&amp;rsquo;ll just deal properly with all the edge cases as they come up&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; you must actively work to divest yourself of these assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; design (universal, accessible, and to some extent pleasing) consists of making as few assumptions as possible about your users.  When design does make excessive assumptions, or false assumptions, it often has the effect of forcing the users to fit the design.  This is upsetting to the users, who (if they have a choice in the matter) may then choose to stop using the product (if it is a product).  However, if the product or design is imposed on the user by an outside force, the resulting effect &amp;ndash; of forcing the user to fit the designer&amp;rsquo;s assumptions &amp;ndash; gets far more dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I wish to do now is provide context: a list of links that have informed and shaped my thinking on this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Epistemological resources to help you on your quest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of prime importance is the concept of legibility, which I first encountered in the SlateStarCodex review of &amp;ldquo;Seeing like a State&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/03/16/book-review-seeing-like-a-state/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Further reading on legibility: &lt;a href=&#34;https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html&#34;&gt;Notes on the Legibility War&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-02-23-09:37.html&#34;&gt;Legibility Privileges&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2020-03-02-09:31.html&#34;&gt;Legibility as a relationship&lt;/a&gt; by D. R. MacIver.  These posts also link to other resources on legibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://notebook.drmaciver.com/posts/2019-06-04-09:58.html&#34;&gt;Notes on the Legibility War&lt;/a&gt; also mentions the idea of torque, which is the &amp;ldquo;force that acts between lives and classification systems, shaping each to the other&amp;rdquo;.  I tend to prefer Siderea&amp;rsquo;s concept of Procrustean Epistemologies: &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1540620.html&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1541132.html&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1548040.html&#34;&gt;Metalogue 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also related is the concept of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Typical_mind_fallacy&#34;&gt;typical mind fallacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots and lots (and lots) of examples of specific problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1430601.html&#34;&gt;Means Tests and Self-Employment&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://siderea.livejournal.com/1220766.html&#34;&gt;De Facto Sexism&lt;/a&gt;, also by Siderea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/talking-microcopy-writing-ux/dear-tech-you-suck-at-delight-86382d101575&#34;&gt;Dear Tech, You Suck at Delight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://meyerweb.com/eric/thoughts/2014/12/24/inadvertent-algorithmic-cruelty/&#34;&gt;Inadvertent Algorithmic Cruelty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sarawb.com/2015/01/13/personal-histories/&#34;&gt;Personal Histories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@maggied/i-tried-tracking-my-period-and-it-was-even-worse-than-i-could-have-imagined-bb46f869f45&#34;&gt;I tried tracking my period and it was even worse than I could have imagined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/feb/23/truth-world-built-for-men-car-crashes&#34;&gt;The deadly truth about a world built for men&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also: the standard computer keyboard key size was designed for men&amp;rsquo;s hands.  There were some experiments in Asia with smaller keyboards, which many women apparently find more comfortable, but they never caught on (and can&amp;rsquo;t even be found in the ergo keyboard market today as far as I&amp;rsquo;m aware, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty obsessive about keyboards).  Like it or not, the standard key size is 19mm, and you&amp;rsquo;re stuck with it even more than you&amp;rsquo;re stuck with QWERTY &amp;ndash; at least layout can be reprogrammed in software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://thefourthvine.tumblr.com/post/81447259791/youre-always-coming-out&#34;&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re Always Coming Out&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to especially call your attention to the quote &amp;ldquo;we only ever fit on forms designed by people like us&amp;rdquo;.  If someone on your team frequently falls into an often-overlooked edge case, they&amp;rsquo;re more likely to notice it in your product.  It&amp;rsquo;s the best practical argument I know of for diversity in the workplace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DataPup_/status/1118516662305685504&#34;&gt;Twitter thread on TSA body scanners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://shinesolutions.com/2018/01/08/falsehoods-programmers-believe-about-names-with-examples/&#34;&gt;Falsehoods Programmers Believe About Names, with examples&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to append to this one the vast number of systems that have trouble dealing with trans people, whose deadnames can often still be their legal names, but who would prefer to be known in all situations by a different chosen name.  Particularly medical and administrative systems, as well as anything that insists on a &amp;ldquo;legal name&amp;rdquo; for no apparent reason.  If you are involved in the design of a system that deals with names, please let the user provide a &amp;ldquo;preferred name&amp;rdquo; that may bear no relation to their legal name, and use the preferred name whenever absolutely possible.  Do not, if you are a doctor&amp;rsquo;s office, shout a patient&amp;rsquo;s deadname to the whole waiting room.  Do not, if you are sending users push notifications or messages, refer to them by deadname in the notification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t have a link for this on hand, but please consider people who&amp;rsquo;ve recently lost their mothers and people who&amp;rsquo;ve cut off toxic or abusive mothers when writing cutesy Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day email copy (similar deal for Father&amp;rsquo;s Day and all other parent- or family-related holidays).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My rant about the FitBit &lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/fitbit/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Indifference towards people and the reality in which they live is actually the one and only cardinal sin in design.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ndash; Dieter Rams&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Custom Keyboard Layout, Part 2</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/keyboard_layout_2/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/keyboard_layout_2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, so my earlier &lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/typewriter_keyboard/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about modifying your keyboard layout sold you, but you don&amp;rsquo;t want to buy a whole new keyboard just yet?  You want a software-side key remapping solution?  Well, sure, fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the long term, this will be more annoying than modifying the keyboard firmware &amp;ndash; as I mentioned before, if you modify the keyboard firmware then you get your layout everywhere you plug in the keyboard, but software-side solutions are specific to the computer you&amp;rsquo;re on.  However, software-side solutions are easier to get started with.  Also you probably don&amp;rsquo;t want to change the firmware on the keyboard embedded in your laptop (for example, if you want to remap capslock to escape, which is one of the earliest items in my new computer setup checklist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Linux: Augh.  If you&amp;rsquo;re using X you can use xkb, for which there are shortcuts to do common modifications like e.g. swap capslock and escape; if you want to do anything more complex be prepared to spend a few hours on it.  I don&amp;rsquo;t use Wayland so I did a quick duckduckgo about it and my eyes went to hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Mac: In later versions of MacOS, System Settings -&amp;gt; Keyboards deigns to allow you to perform a shortlist of modifications (e.g. swap capslock and escape).  For anything more advanced you&amp;rsquo;ll want Karabiner, which I seriously can&amp;rsquo;t recommend enough.  Comes with two tools: Karabiner Elements (set your remappings) and Karabiner Element Viewer (shows you what input events your keyboard is sending, which is great for debugging keyboard firmware).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows: Use AutoHotKey.  I don&amp;rsquo;t know shit about AHK because the last* Windows computer I ever used was the desktop my dad helped me build when I was like 9 that dual-booted Windows XP and the educational edition of Ubuntu.  However, Hillel Wayne has a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hillelwayne.com/post/ahk/&#34;&gt;great post about it&lt;/a&gt; that you might want to refer to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*This is not quite true.  Briefly, at a past internship, I had to use a Windows 10 computer because I was using a motion-capture system and its software was Windows-only.  I hated it.  Cortana kept yelling at me??  Things were happening seemingly uncontrollably?  How does anyone put up with this?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Google Calendar Time Tracker</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/gcal_tracker/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/gcal_tracker/</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post was originally written in spring of 2019, when I&amp;rsquo;d just created the time tracker.  In the interim, Google seems to have changed their auth flow, and I can no longer get the tracker to work &amp;ndash; not that I tried very hard, in all honesty.  It&amp;rsquo;s undocumented and hastily written, and I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily recommend trying to reuse my code.  Nevertheless, I still like the idea!  Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll rewrite it some day&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar Time Tracker is a simple command-line utility that displays time breakdowns for the tasks on my Google Calendar, grouped by calendar and optionally by name.  For example, I can compute the total time of the events in my calendar for 6.832 (Underactuated Robotics) for the past week, and also check what portion of this time was spent on homework or in class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this to track how much time I spend on each of my classes, but it&amp;rsquo;s flexible enough to be useful as a generic time tracker for contractors billing by the hour, interns working an hourly wage, or anyone else that wants to check how they&amp;rsquo;re spending their time. You can find it on my github &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shilohc/gcal-tracker&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/gcal_tracker.png&#34; alt=&#34;Screenshot of Google Calendar with an inset showing the output of my time tracker&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above is my calendar for the week, with an inset showing some of the time tracker&amp;rsquo;s output for this week&amp;rsquo;s planned schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>H-NAV</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/hnav/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/hnav/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The H-NAV is a LIDAR-based navigational aid for visually impaired people. The LIDAR detects obstacles within two meters that are approximately at face height, and a set of vibrating motors in the hatband indicates the obstacles&#39; direction and rough distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project went through three major versions, each revision prompted by user tests. I tested the first two versions on myself and other sighted users, and was also able to test the third version on a group of blind volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/hnav.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Picture of the H-NAV.  It&amp;rsquo;s a light brown cowboy hat with a LiDAR mounted on the top and a PCB with a knob and slider on the side.  It is sitting on a white foam display head.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictured above is the third revision of the H-NAV. A PCB mounted on the side of the hat contains a slider for adjusting the obstacle distance threshold. The main PCB, tucked under the LIDAR, contains an ATMega324 microprocessor for processing LIDAR data and the lithium-ion battery charging circuitry, and the vibrating motors are mounted to a flexible PCB inside the hatband containing a second microprocessor, the ATTiny2313.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The H-NAV was my science fair project from 2013 to 2015, and won numerous awards, including Project of the Year at the California State Science Fair, National Finalist at the Junior Science and Humanities Symposium, and Regional Finalist for the Americas at the Google Science Fair. It was also featured in Popular Mechanics (winner of a Next Generation Breakthrough Award) and on the Today Show (winner of a Make the Future Award).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video controls name=&#34;media&#34;&gt;
  &lt;source src=https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/todayshow.mp4#t&amp;#61;290 type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;Transcript of relevant segment, 4:50 - 6:05&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HOST: Let&amp;rsquo;s move over to our last one.  This is Shiloh, she&amp;rsquo;s 15, from Sunnyvale, California.  Shiloh, what did you invent here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: So, it&amp;rsquo;s a hat for the blind that detects face-level obstacles, and indicates them to the user using an array of vibrating motors inside the hatband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: May I try one on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: Sure, why don&amp;rsquo;t you try this on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: Oh, you&amp;rsquo;re going to let me try yours?  Okay.  Hey, give me an idea of how this works.  I have a giant head, and there&amp;rsquo;s nothing I can do about that, but &amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[LAUGHTER]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: Okay.  So what &amp;ndash; how does it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: So you&amp;rsquo;re going to start feeling vibrating motors all around your head &amp;ndash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: Oh my gosh, I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: &amp;ndash; corresponding to where the obstacles are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: I sense you over here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: So if you can feel my hand over here, you should be able to find &amp;ndash; feel it moving towards your front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: That is remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: And these LEDs I put on this hat for demonstration also show the vibration pulses of the motors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: How was this idea born?  How&amp;rsquo;d you come up with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SHILOH: So that&amp;rsquo;s kind of an interesting story.  One day I was demonstrating one of my robots to some children and I used an analogy like, a robot is blind until you put sensors on it, to explain how sensors are used.  And then a while later I was attending a presentation given by Brian Higgins, a blind rehabilitation specialist, and he was describing his idea for a robot guide dog, and I was thinking, why don&amp;rsquo;t we put sensors on the blind so they can navigate like robots?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HOST: It&amp;rsquo;s brilliant, and I sense you right now, it&amp;rsquo;s vibrating.  Congratulations Shiloh, it&amp;rsquo;s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Sting Operation</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/sting_operation/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/sting_operation/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sting Operation is a homebrew telepresence robot; my original intent was to use it to attend &lt;a href=&#34;http://hbrobotics.org/&#34;&gt;robot club&lt;/a&gt; when I&amp;rsquo;m away at MIT.  Currently, it&amp;rsquo;s outfitted with a Neato BotVac LiDAR, a Raspberry Pi running ROS, and a PyBoard controlling the motors and LIDAR. An iPad mounted on a tripod lets me FaceTime the robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/stingoperation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Picture of Sting Operation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictured above: Sting Operation base (minus tripod). It&amp;rsquo;s a two-wheeled base with a castor wheel.  There is also a RC receiver that can be used for local teleoperation, and a dial on the front of the robot indicating its state (under remote control, under local control, stopped, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Typewriter Keyboard</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/typewriter_keyboard/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/typewriter_keyboard/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a mechanical keyboard build (DZ60 PCB, Kailh Box Navy switches) that uses as its keycaps real keys from old typewriters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/typewriter_kb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Picture of typewriter keyboard without case, with more typewriter keys clustered near it&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used three different sets of vintage typewriter keys. The alpha keys and some of the modifiers are glass tombstone-style keys from a vintage Royal mechanical typewriter, but since that&amp;rsquo;s only 50 keys, I augmented it with plastic keys from two different sets (origin unknown).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: Old typewriters &amp;ndash; including the Royal that my keys are from &amp;ndash; often didn&amp;rsquo;t come with a &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; key; instead, the digit &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; was typed using a lowercase &lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These keys came with part of the typewriter stem still attached to the back, which I had to trim to a reasonable length. I cut a few off with a dremel tool, but this was more time-consuming than I liked, so I used a sheet metal hand nibbler on the rest and gave myself a wicked hand cramp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I designed (in OnShape) and 3D-printed adapters for these keys that would fit on the Cherry MX switches.  These, I hot-glued to the typewriter keys. I ended up designing six or so types of adapters &amp;ndash; some of the metal keys had wider stems than the others, a few came without stems, and of course each set of plastic keys needed its own type of adapter.  If I re-did this project I might use a material other than hot-melt glue to attach the adapters to the plastic keys; a couple of the keycaps I used on my arrow keys have an alarming tendency to come loose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t really think far enough ahead to design and lasercut a custom plate, so I decided to do a plateless build with PCB-mount switches. Problem: Kailh BOX Navy switches aren&amp;rsquo;t PCB-mount. (PCB-mount switches have, in addition to the two metal switch pins, two plastic pins that fit into holes on the PCB for added rigidity.) Therefore, I hot-glued them to the PCB. A lot of hot glue was involved in this build.  I then mounted the finished PCB in a 3D-printed case from Thingiverse (I believe &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:962978&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;ve long since misplaced the original link).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/typewriter_kb2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Picture of typewriter keyboard with case&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final step was flashing the keyboard firmware. Thankfully, the DZ60 is one of the incredibly many keyboards supported by the open-source QMK keyboard firmware. I tweaked one of the standard layouts a bit, since I&amp;rsquo;m using a somewhat weird split-spacebar layout with arrow keys. I also customized the underglow LED lighting and started adding some interesting layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s still more to do with this project.  I primarily want to work on the firmware; &lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/keyboard_layout/&#34;&gt;programming my Preonic&lt;/a&gt; has given me a much better idea of what I want on my layers.  Also, my 3D-printed case is lovely and purple, but it is also unfortunately opaque, and blocks most of the underglow LEDs &amp;ndash; it would be nice to replace the back of the case with acrylic, so the light can actually get outside the case, instead of shining up through the unpopulated holes in the PCB.  But for now, the keyboard works just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Custom Keyboard Layout</title>
        <link>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/keyboard_layout/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/keyboard_layout/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s no secret that I&amp;rsquo;m massively obsessed with mechanical keyboards.  For sheer customizability, they&amp;rsquo;re impossible to beat.  Yes, I can put a lot of effort into software key remappings and then carefully port them over to every new computer I use &amp;ndash; or I can just use open-source keyboard firmware &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.qmk.fm/#/&#34;&gt;QMK&lt;/a&gt; and my keyboard will work wherever I plug it in.  QMK also lets me program keys to do one thing when tapped and another thing when held down, or configure &amp;ldquo;layers&amp;rdquo; so that my letter keys will turn into symbol keys, so it&amp;rsquo;s more powerful than software configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can I exercise this power for myself, I hear you ask?  First, get a keyboard that supports QMK.  I personally use a Preonic, which is not for everyone, but I recommend that you get a keyboard that has a split spacebar or otherwise has some extra thumb keys &amp;ndash; these are very convenient to assign as &amp;ldquo;layer activation&amp;rdquo; keys.  Then, follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.qmk.fm/#/newbs&#34;&gt;QMK docs&lt;/a&gt; on making a new keymap file and flashing your keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/preonic1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Preonic, with its original keycaps&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll notice that the Preonic has a &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; key to the left of the spacebar and a &amp;ldquo;raise&amp;rdquo; key to the right.  These let you easily access &amp;ldquo;raise&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;lower&amp;rdquo; layers by holding down the respective key &amp;ndash; instantly and enormously expanding your keyboard.  It also has actual, physical arrow keys, something that&amp;rsquo;s important to me, and yet it takes up less space than a normal 60% keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post will be about my personal layout choices.  You may want to follow along by looking at my personal config, which is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shilohc/qmk_firmware/tree/shilohc/keymaps/keyboards/preonic/keymaps/shilohc&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  You can find all my personal QMK configs in my fork of QMK &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shilohc/qmk_firmware/tree/shilohc/keymaps&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  I also have a custom config for a DZ60, which is the PCB I used for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/posts/typewriter_keyboard/&#34;&gt;typewriter keyboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/preonic2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Preonic, with Tengwar DSA keycaps&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the default layer, labeled &lt;code&gt;_QWERTY&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;keymap.c&lt;/code&gt;.  I haven&amp;rsquo;t made too many changes here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete key changed to backslash because I write a lot of LaTeX and don&amp;rsquo;t use delete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capslock changed to escape, something I highly recommend to all vim users.  If you use emacs I would instead suggest remapping it to ctrl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Enter key has been changed to &lt;code&gt;SFT_T(KC_ENT)&lt;/code&gt;.  If it&amp;rsquo;s held down, and another key is pressed, it functions as a shift; if tapped, it acts as enter.  This is because when I first switched to the Preonic I exclusively used the right shift key, which the Preonic doesn&amp;rsquo;t have.  I now use the left shift more often on my preonic, but on my Macbook&amp;rsquo;s rubber keyboard cover, there&amp;rsquo;s still a massive wear spot in the right shift while the left shift is near-pristine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;_LOWER&lt;/code&gt; layer is the one I&amp;rsquo;ve customized the most &amp;ndash; this is now my &amp;ldquo;symbols and function keys&amp;rdquo; layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The symbols that usually live on the number keys, &lt;code&gt;!@#$%^&amp;amp;*()&lt;/code&gt;, have been moved to the top row of letters, and the other common programming symbols live on the home row.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All three sets of brackets (parentheses, square-brackets, and curlyboys) are in a vertical stack on the rightmost columns of letter keys.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backslash stays the same, but pipe (&lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;) has been moved to the quote key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll notice that the little diagram in the comments says Squid on it.  I was experimenting with QMK&amp;rsquo;s Unicode-sending functionality, something the USB HID device standard typically doesn&amp;rsquo;t allow, by using this key to send the squid kaomoji, &lt;code&gt;くコ:彡&lt;/code&gt;.  Unfortunately, it didn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;_RAISE&lt;/code&gt; layer is for special commands, since I moved all the symbol functionality into &lt;code&gt;_LOWER&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;H, J, K, L can be used to drive the mouse around, and the semicolon key sends a click.  U and I scroll down and up.  This is probably the functionality on this layer I use most often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I experimented with using several other keys on this layer to control brightness, music, etc., but honestly I mostly don&amp;rsquo;t use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;code&gt;_ADJUST&lt;/code&gt; layer, which I never use (except once, when I was randomly button-mashing and accidentally switched into Colemak).  The less said about this, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/preonic3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The Preonic, with Godspeed MT3 keycaps&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the default keymap, both raise and lower have all the function keys on them, which is wasteful.  In addition, raise has a few symbols on it, in the same place where the lower layer also has symbols, which was really confusing for me to learn &amp;ndash; I could never remember whether the symbol I wanted was on raise or lower.  And some of the symbols were just hard to reach, especially &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; which I type a lot in bash commands.  With all the symbols on the raise layer, the functionality is (mostly) neatly divided into &amp;ldquo;symbols layer&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;not symbols layer&amp;rdquo;, which is easier to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to stick to the QWERTY layout rather than switch to Dvorak or Colemak or Workman or something, mostly because I use vim and don&amp;rsquo;t want to disrupt that muscle memory.  (One afternoon I decided to try out Dvorak &amp;ndash; my typing speed after a few hours of practice wasn&amp;rsquo;t terrible, but then I tried to edit something in vim and I went directly to hell.  It was like, things are happening!  Why have I just jumped to the start of the file and deleted a bunch of lines?  That&amp;rsquo;s not what I wanted!)  I find that even with QWERTY, my Preonic represents a significant ergonomic improvement over a standard keyboard, since it&amp;rsquo;s ortholinear and very compact, reducing the distance my fingers have to stretch &amp;ndash; and my custom layout improves things more by putting all the symbols under the top two rows of letters.  Your mileage, of course, may vary.  A keyboard layout is a very personal thing, and I encourage you to experiment and customize yours until it perfectly fits you and your needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://shilohc.github.io/blog/img/keyboard_layout_meme.png&#34; alt=&#34;a keyboard layout is something that can actually be so personal&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>

